<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>A briefe and cleare confession of the Christian fayth Containing an hundreth articles, after the order of the creede of the Apostles. Made and declared by Iohn Gardiner. Translated out of French into English by Iohn Brooke of Asshe, next Sandwitch. An. 1577.</title>
            <title>Briefve et claire confession de la foy chrestienne. English.</title>
            <author>Garnier, Jean, d. 1574.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1579</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 153 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 65 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2013-12">2013-12 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A01445</idno>
            <idno type="STC">STC 11565</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC S92644</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99848059</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99848059</idno>
            <idno type="VID">13133</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A01445)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 13133)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1475-1640 ; 243:09)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>A briefe and cleare confession of the Christian fayth Containing an hundreth articles, after the order of the creede of the Apostles. Made and declared by Iohn Gardiner. Translated out of French into English by Iohn Brooke of Asshe, next Sandwitch. An. 1577.</title>
                  <title>Briefve et claire confession de la foy chrestienne. English.</title>
                  <author>Garnier, Jean, d. 1574.</author>
                  <author>Brooke, John, d. 1582.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[12], 48, [4] leaves   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>[By J. Charlewood] for Edward Wight [i.e. White], and are to be sold at his shop at the little North doore of Paules, at the signe of the Gun,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>Imprinted at London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1579.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>A translation of: Garnier, Jean.  Briefve et claire confession de la foy chrestienne, contenant cent articles, selon l'ordre du symbole des apostres.</note>
                  <note>Formerly STC 11565.</note>
                  <note>Identified as STC 11565 on UMI microfilm.</note>
                  <note>Printer's name and vendor's actual name from STC.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the Bodleian Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Apostles' Creed --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2012-09</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-09</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-11</date>
            <label>Olivia Bottum</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-11</date>
            <label>Olivia Bottum</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-02</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:13133:1"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:13133:1"/>
            <p>
               <g ref="char:leaf">❧</g> 
               <hi>A briefe and cleare <hi>Confeſſion of the</hi> Chriſtian Fayth.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Containing An hundreth Articles, <hi>af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter the order of the Creede of</hi>
               </hi> the Apoſtles.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Made and declared by <hi>Iohn Gardiner.</hi>
               </hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Tranſlated out of French into</hi> Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liſh by <hi>Iohn Brooke</hi> of Aſſhe, next Sandwitch. <hi>An. 1577.</hi>
            </p>
            <q>
               <bibl>
                  <hi>Rom. 10.</hi>
               </bibl>
               <p>¶ The beliefe of the hart iuſtifieth, but to confeſſe with the mouth maketh a man ſafe.</p>
            </q>
            <p>
               <hi>Imprinted at London for Edward</hi> Wight, and are to be ſold at his ſhop at the litle North doore of <hi>Paules,</hi> at the ſigne of the Gun. <hi>1579.</hi>
            </p>
         </div>
         <div type="dedication">
            <pb facs="tcp:13133:2"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:13133:2"/>
            <head>
               <hi>
                  <g ref="char:leaf">❧</g> To the Right Honora<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble Syr William Cecill Knight,</hi> Ba<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ron of Burgley, Knight of the <hi>Ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>norable order of the Garter, Maſter of</hi> her Highneſſe Wardes and Liue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ries, one of the Lordes of her Maieſties priuy Counſell, and Lorde high Treaſoror of England.</head>
            <p>
               <hi>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">R</seg>Eading this ſmall</hi> litle Volume, fyrſt writ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten in French, and collec<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted by Maiſter Iohn Gar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diner (right honorable) and perceiuing the ſame in my ſimple iudgement, vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der a poore habite and litle ſhowe, to beare and importe great and waigh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty effect, finding alſo therin ſuch ſingu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ler ground of profound learning and rare wiſdome, and therewithall ſuch firme approbations and inexpugna<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble
<pb facs="tcp:13133:3"/> defences, with authorities of holy writ, I thought it no leſſe then neede<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full, and nothing more then neceſſary to doo what in me mightlye, to make the ſame, obuious, vſuall and familyer vnto my brethren of this Realme, by tranſlating the ſame into our mother tongue. The which thing hauing once perfourmed and finiſhed, according to my poore talent, and ſclender ſkill: al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>though I doo not doubt to haue fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowed myne Authour directlye and truly in ſence and expoſition, without corruption or abuſe: yet finding in my ſelfe ſuch imperfections of learning, ſuch barrennes and want of fine Phraſe and choiſe wordes wherwith to haue garniſhed the ſame, vnneathes I durſt of my ſelfe, or in myne owne name, launch foorth my ſilly barke into the troubleſom waues, not doubting (ſaile ſhe neuer ſo ſure &amp; true) but ſomtimes ſhee ſhalbe countermet with churliſhe
<pb facs="tcp:13133:3"/> byllowes, and puffed at with outragi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous blaſtes and violent tempeſtes. The force wherof more ſafely to defend and withſtand, being loth to leaue the ſame in ſuch obſcureneſſe and ſecrecy, as I found it, whereof no Chriſtian man ought to be ignorant, I imagined with my ſelfe to ſeeke to ancor in your har<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>borough, being very deſirous that this my vnſmoothed and roughe hewen workemanſhippe might haue free paſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſage and ſafe conduct vnder your Ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nors fauorable protection and defe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce. In which purpoſe and pretence, being abaſhed and more then halfe diſmaied, by the occaſions aforeſaid: yet grewe I in double hart and tooke treble encou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ragement, that the authoritye of the matter it ſelfe would more then coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teruaile the reſt in your Honors fauo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rable acceptaunce. But when I further conſidered, wherof I ſhould craue you to be a ſupporter, namely of the Chriſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tian
<pb facs="tcp:13133:4"/> fayth (for ſo the Booke is intitu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led, and contayneth an hundreth Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticles of the Chriſtian fayth) all feare<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full doubtes expelled, aſſured truſte willed mee to abyde conſtant in my purpoſe. For as to your Honorable tytle, Wiſdome hath annexed her en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>largement of Authoritye: ſo to that Authoritye, godlye zeale hauing ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ioined a feruencie of true fayth, and to theſe alſo humilitye of ſpirite, hauing coupled franke curteſye and beneuo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lence towardes all: Theſe I ſaye, right Honorable haue made me ſo bolde to craue that this my ſmall peece of tra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uaile, whatſoeuer, maye receyue that hope hath promyſed, and with my good will would gladlye deſerue be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing no wayes able, excepte by prayer to almyghtye GOD, on whome as dutye byndeth I ſhall not ceaſe con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tynually to call for your Lordſhippes
<pb facs="tcp:13133:4"/> long preſeruation of lyfe, and much encreaſe of his moſte comfor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>table bleſſinges.</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>Your Honors day<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly Orator <hi>Iohn Brooke.</hi>
               </signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
         <div type="author_to_the_reader">
            <pb facs="tcp:13133:5"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:13133:5"/>
            <head>
               <g ref="char:leaf">❧</g> 
               <hi>Iohn Gardiner vnto <hi>all the litle French Church</hi> of Straſburg, aſſembled together</hi> for the Goſpell, in the name of <hi>Ieſus Chriſt: grace, peace and mercie of</hi> the Father through Ieſus Chriſte our Lorde, onely Sauior and redéemer, in the vertue of the holy Spirite, be geuen vnto you eter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nally. <hi>Amen.</hi>
            </head>
            <p>
               <hi>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">W</seg>Hen I conſider the</hi> cleare lightes, the great ingenyous and ſharpe wittes, which the Lorde in our time hath placed in his Church (déerely beloued brethren and welbeloued in Ieſus Chriſte) who neuer ceaſe day nor night to aduaunce the glorye of God, and to promote the kingdome of Ieſus Chriſte his ſonne, aſwell by their wordes, as writing, of whome I am not worthy to be a Diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciple. I am aſhamed and feare leſt I be iudged raiſh to put my hand to the pen after them, and chiefly for to entreat of
<pb facs="tcp:13133:6"/> thinges ſo litle and common, the which they haue entreated of in theyr Cate<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chiſmes from the beginning. But the holy deſire of you and of manye other good brethren, who hauing heard open<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly the reading of this litle Treatiſe, in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtantly requiring to be pertakers haue incited, yea conſtrained mee to do it, with the great deſire that I haue of the aduauncement of the glory of God and of the health of all my brethren: Know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing that God would haue al the world to come vnto the knowledg of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> trueth,<note place="margin">1. Tim. 2.</note> and by that meanes to be ſaued. I know alſo that for the building of the Lordes tabernacle made by <hi>Moyſes,</hi>
               <note place="margin">S. Ierom. Exo. 25.</note> euery one brought that he had, ſome golde and ſil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer, others precious ſtones, others lin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nen cloth, goates and buckes ſkinnes, others wood, and common ſtones, and all of it was ſet a worke: So I eſtéeme, for the building of this houſe of the Lorde,<note place="margin">1. Cor. 3. Ephe. 4.</note> which is his Church, euery one may and ought to bring that y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> he hath, ſome more, ſome leſſe, according to the tallentes which the Lorde of the houſe hath geuen them, I wil content my ſelf to carry litle common ſtones for this
<pb facs="tcp:13133:6"/> building, and do hope that the Maſter worke men will not reiect my ſeruice, nor my litle ſtones, ſo that they be fitte for the building (as I hope they ſhalbe, God ayding me.<note place="margin">Math. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>. Luke. 21.</note>) The poore wydowe which did put into the box but two litle peeces of ſiluer, was not reiected nor de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpiſed of the Lorde, but was as much prayſed as the great ritch men which gaue a great deale more then ſhe. All that being well conſidered hath mooued me to ſet forth this litle treatiſe in this tyme chiefly, in which the Lorde hath the ſiue in his hand to ſifte, examine, and repurge his Church, in which it ſhould be verye good (in my iudgment) that euerye mans fayth ſhould be kno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wen, and chieflye of thoſe which make profeſſion of the Goſpell, for to teach o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers, as are the Doctors and Miniſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ers of the word, that the falſe Prophets and Hypocrites which doo bowe theyr ſhoulders and leane theyr eares vnto falſe papiſticall doctrine of Antechriſte ſhould be knowne, driued and chaſed a way from the good &amp; faythful. For that cauſe I am conte<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t, y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> my faith, in which I will lyue and dye thorow the grace
<pb facs="tcp:13133:7"/> of the Lord be knowen of al the world.</p>
            <p>Now this litle Treatiſe ſhall haue much neede of a ſecond which ſhal geue the reaſon of that that this here confeſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeth, for it is one thing to confeſſe the fayth, and another to geue a reaſon of the fayth. To confeſſe the fayth, that is purely, ſymply, and clearely, to ſay, and confeſſe with hart and mouth, or by writing that that one beléeueth of God and <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> 
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>is word. But to geue a reaſon of the fayth is to prooue and openly to ſhew by teres of the holy ſcripture, and manifeſt reaſons grou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ded in the ſame, what one beléeueth, and wherfore one beléeueth, as Saint <hi>Peter</hi>
               <note place="margin">1. Peter. 3.</note> the Apoſtle commaundeth. The which I haue made in tymes paſt, in the time of the faires, (as you haue heard and vnder<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtood) in declaring that confeſſion by Articles, for to geue ſome lytle taſte of the Goſpell vnto the ſtraingers which came hether, and to make them to vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derſtand, what is our faith and religio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> in which we wil liue and dye, and that we are not heretickes, ſeditious nor blaſphemers (as many do eſtéeme vs to be) but faithfull and true Chriſtians,
<pb facs="tcp:13133:7"/> hauing and receyuing one onely Ieſus Chriſt for our Lord, Sauiour, Media<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tour and Aduocate, beleeuing &amp; hoping in him only, and not in any other, for which alſo we wil venter and ieopard not onely our externall goods, but alſo our bodyes vnto the laſt droppe of our bloud.<note place="margin">Mat. 10.16 Mark. 8. Luke. 9.17.</note> Knowing that whoſoeuer ſhall looſe his life for the loue of him, ſhall fynde it, and he that will kéepe it in re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nouncing and forſaking him, he ſhall looſe it eternally. This hath beene my marke and principall end, all that time there, in which I had not (nor haue yet at this preſent) the leiſure to collect and put in wryting all the probation argu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments &amp; reaſons, which I haue vſed aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wel of the holy ſcriptures as of the aun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cie<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t fathers for to yeeld a reaſon of my faith, &amp; to ſhew the truth of the articles therof therein contained. But if y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> Lord do geue vs good peace, and keepe vs yet ſtil in this place (as I hope y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> he will do thorowe his mercy, although we haue not merited it) I promiſe to geue vnto you y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſecond treatiſe correſponda<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t vnto this here, in which I wil geue y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> reaſon of my faith, as in this I wil declare and
<pb facs="tcp:13133:8"/> confeſſe (with the helpe of the Lord (the verity of all theſe Articles which are in number an hundreth, aſwell by the word of God, as by the writings of the auncient Fathers, according to my li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tle faculty &amp; the grace which the Lord ſhall geue me, and then I will content my ſelf that I haue liued in this world. In the meane time deere brethren, I praye you to receyue and take in good part this litle gifte and preſent, of the hand of your lawful brother and faith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full friend, hoping to receiue a greater. I aſſure you that the onely word of the Lord is the fayre and large garden of pleaſure, within which I putting my ſelfe, haue gathered theſe goodly ſwéete ſmelling flowers, and made this fayre garlande of triumphe, for to put it vp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on the heads of the true faithfull Chriſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tians (ſuch as now are.) And I haue ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken nothing from the ſinke, puddle and takes of <hi>Luiterim,</hi> nor from other ſuch like papiſticall doctrines, Antechriſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ans and inuentions of men. For out of ſuch ſinkes puddles and infections ſuch flowers ſpring not forth, but rather thornes bryers and thyſtles for to fede
<pb facs="tcp:13133:8"/> and crowne the Aſſes of Antechriſte.</p>
            <p>I may boldlye ſaye, that there is no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing in this litle Treatiſe, but that I can ſhew and prooue it by the worde of God, the which I haue folowed and not the diuers opinions of men: For I haue not ſworne in any mans word, but in that ſame of Ieſus Chriſte, vpon which my fayth is builded, and not vpon the opinion of men: therfore I haue ſpoken here and written freelye that which I féele in my harte, without hauing re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gard vnto any other then vnto my on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly Lord and Maſter Ieſus Chriſte.</p>
            <p>This may ſerue at all tymes for a paterne &amp; rule of the confeſſion of faith, to all thoſe which wyll declare them ſelues to be of the number of our aſſem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bly following the holye cuſtome &amp; moſt allowable, of this litle Church, that all thoſe which will perticipate or commu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nicate with vs in the holye table of the Lorde, firſte of all ought to make pub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>like confeſſion of their fayth, that is to ſaye: to declare before the aſſembly the fayth and knowledge, which the Lorde hath geuen vnto them of the word and Goſpell of his ſonne Ieſus Chriſt, that
<pb facs="tcp:13133:9"/> they may be knowen and manyfeſted vnto all the congregation, to be of the number of the faithfull and true mem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bers of Chriſt, worthy to perticipat of the giftes, graces and benefits of the Lord with the brethren. As alſo of late vnder the lawe all ſtraungers which would communicate or perticipate the paſcall Lambe with the people of Iſra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ell,<note place="margin">Exo. 12.</note> ought firſt to renounce all Idolatry to receiue circumciſion, &amp; to make pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſion of all the lawe, and religion of God, geuen by <hi>Moyſes,</hi> promiſing to liue and walk in the ſame all the daies of their life: And by that meanes were admitted to the Paſſeouer, to eate and communicate with the other, and not otherwiſe.<note place="margin">Exo. 12.</note> As it is written in the booke of the lawe. Truly it is more to perti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cipat in the holy table of the Lord (that is to ſay in the holy Sacrament of the Supper) the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> to eat the paſcall Lambe: for ſomuch as the cleereneſſe is more then the ſhadow,<note place="margin">Heb. 10. Colloſ. 2.</note> and the verity more then the figure: For the lawe was but the ſhadow and figure of the verity, the which we haue preſent before vs. If the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> there were vnder the law obſerued
<pb facs="tcp:13133:9"/> and kept ſuch diſcipline in the Churche of God, among the faithfull, how much more ought it to be obſerued vnder the verety in the ſhéepfold of Ieſus Chriſt, which is his Church?<note place="margin">Ioh. 10. Exo. 20. 1. Pet. 5. Math. 7.15</note> who commaun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deth the ſhepheardes thereof to knowe the ſheepe, and call them by their name, and diligently to conſider theyr eſtate, leſt they ſhould geue y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> childrens bread vnto dogs, and the pearles vnto hogs. Then as <hi>Moyſes</hi> the ſeruaunt of God did not admit vnto the Paſſeouer anye ſtraungers, before they firſte declared their faith: ſo the good &amp; faythfull eccle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiaſtical paſtor, ought not to admit (ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to my aduiſe, ſaued alwayes a better iudgement) vnto the holy table any ſtraungers, whoſe fayth is vnto him vnknowe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, but to endeuor him ſelf firſte to knowe their fayth and religi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on by all meanes priuately and perti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>culerly, if he cannot publikelye before the Churche and Congregation, that he maye witneſſe of theyr fayth before all the brethren: And by that meanes to admytte them with the other.</p>
            <p>This pollycye and lowable diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciplyne, was kepte and obſerued in
<pb facs="tcp:13133:10"/> this our litle Church (as you knowe) from the beginning, vnto this daye: The Lorde thorowe his grace, graunt that it may long continue, to the praiſe of his name: For by the ſame many ig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>noraunt are taught, in the rudimentes of the Chriſtian faith: And there know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge is alwaies augmented, and there is none of vs but receiueth great profit. To this then this litle Treatiſe maye well ſerue for a patterne and rule (as it is ſayd) for the young ones, ſimple and ignoraunt, who maye take what they thinke good and leaue the reſt for to a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uoyd prolixity: therfore I haue deuided and diſtinguiſhed it by Articles. Fur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thermore, this Confeſſion is deuided in to foure principall poyntes: In the firſt I ſhew what I beleeue of the holy Tri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nitie, chiefly of the eternall Father and of the thinges made by him, of the firſt creation of man, and of his fall: In the ſecond what I beléeue of the Sonne which is the ſecond perſon, and of the thinges by him made, chiefly of the re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>payring and reſtoring of man: In the third, what I beléeue of the holy ghoſt, which is the thirde perſon of the holye
<pb facs="tcp:13133:10"/> Trynitie by whom man (made by the Father, and reſtored by the Sonne) is mayntained and kept in his being: In the fourth, what I beléeue of the holy Catholike Church, and of the thinges concerning the ſame. That doon, I ſhew and declare the great frutes proceeding and comming from that fayth, whiche are thrée in number, as you may ſee to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wardes the ende: And all of it is made after the order of the ſimbole or creede, which we call commonly the Apoſtles creede, which hath bene receiued at all tymes without any contraduction in the Catholike Church. And let no man maruaile, although I multiplye theſe Articles vnto an hundreth, although that the Créede containeth but twelue: For euery one of the twelue, contay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neth other twelue and more. Doo then as the honnye Bées, who of all flowers doo gather profit: By that meanes you ſhall augment more and more in fayth and knowledg of the Lord, &amp; in charity and loue towardes your neyghbours, for therein dependeth all the lawe and the Prophets. I beſéeche that good God and celeſtiall father which hath deliue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red
<pb facs="tcp:13133:11"/> you from the tirraunye of Ante<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chriſte, and hath drawne you from darkneſſe, error and ignorance, open<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing your inward eyes, declaring him ſelfe vnto you by his Goſpell, that it would pleaſe him to augment alwaies his giftes, graces and benedictions in you, to direct and keepe you by his holy ſpirite. Vnto eternall life, in the name of his ſonne Ieſus Chriſte our Lord and one-Sauiour. <hi>Amen.</hi>
            </p>
            <closer>
               <dateline>
                  <hi>From Straſburg.</hi> 
                  <date>24. <hi>Iuly.</hi> 1549.</date>
               </dateline>
            </closer>
         </div>
         <div type="translator_to_the_reader">
            <pb facs="tcp:13133:11"/>
            <head>
               <hi>¶ Iohn Brooke</hi> to the Chriſtian Reader.</head>
            <p>
               <hi>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>His litle Pamph<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>let</hi> (gentle Reader) may ſeeme vnto thee a thing of ſmall value and leſſe importance, if thou make thy eſtima<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion thereof by the ſmall outwarde ſhowe and feeling: But if in this litle and light worke to the eye, be enclu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded great and waighty matter, if in this briefe and ſhort Treatiſe be wrap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ped and ſufficiently ſet forth long and manifold cauſes, how much the more then is it to be imbraced and eſtemed. I promyſe thee nothing, but for gra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mrecye, offer thee my good wyll and trauaile, I red it in French, written by maſter Iohn Gardiner: and finding it pithy, profitable and neceſſary to bee red of all Chriſtians, for thine onelye commodity and comfort I haue tran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſlated him into thy mother tongue. If
<pb facs="tcp:13133:12"/> in this tranſlation thou finde any im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perfection, let my zeale &amp; good mea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning towardes thee, counteruaile or rather preuaile to gaine thy friendly acceptaunce, and do not therein con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>demne the thing or the Authour, who vndoubtedly needeth no ſupporter or defender, but bringeth with him mu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nition and defence ſufficient. But ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uenture (I ſay) the reading as I did at the firſte, if thou finde him worthye, make it a Iewell vnto thee, beare him daily in thy hand, or button him nere thy hart in thy boſo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, he is neither hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uy nor cu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>brous, nor wil be vnto thee very chargeable. Gods holy ſpirite be thy guide in reading and vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derſtanding, to the eſtabliſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment and confirmati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of thy Chriſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>an faith. Fare<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>well.</p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="text">
            <pb facs="tcp:13133:12"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:13133:13"/>
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:13133:13"/>
            <head>
               <g ref="char:leaf">❧</g> A briefe and cleare <hi>Confeſsion, of the Chriſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>an</hi> Fayth: contayning a <hi>hun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dreth Articles, after the order of</hi> the Apoſtles Creede.</head>
            <div type="commentary">
               <head>I beleeue in GOD, the Father almightye, maker of Heauen and Earth.</head>
               <div n="1" type="article">
                  <head>The .1. Article.</head>
                  <p>
                     <hi>
                        <seg rend="decorInit">F</seg>Irſt of al,</hi>
                     <note place="margin">Deut. 6. Eſa. 6.45. Mala. 2. Gene. 1. Pſ. 33.101. Eſa. 64. Iere. 23. Actes. 4.17</note> 
                     <hi>I beleue</hi> in one GOD, onely in eſſence and ſubſtaunce, thrée in perſon, the Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, the Sonne and the holy Ghoſt. The Father as the Ori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ginall and beginning of all thinges, aſwell viſible as inuiſible: Of whome alſo they depende, aſwell in their be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing as conſeruation. And he dependeth not but of him ſelfe, eternall, without ende and without beginning.<note place="margin">Pſa. 2.110, Iohn. 1.3, 5, 14.</note> The Sonne, as the heauenly worde, the
<pb facs="tcp:13133:14"/> ſapience and wiſdome of the Father,<note place="margin">Math. 3.17 Luke. 3.</note> which is eternally &amp; before al worlds, begotten of the Father of his proper ſubſtaunce and nature: Becauſe that in him ſhineth his proper carecter &amp; I<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mage, otherwiſe inuiſible vnto y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> mor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tall man.<note place="margin">2. Cor. 4. Coloſ. 1. Hebre. 1. Pſ. 51.143 Ioh. 3.14.15.16.</note> The holy Ghoſt, as the ver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tue and eternall power, which is ney<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther made nor created, nor begotten, but proceeding from the father and the Sonne eternally, as alone proceeding of two perſons.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="2" type="article">
                  <head>
                     <note place="margin">Deut. 4.23 Eſa. 44.45. Ioh. 1.5.10 Exod 20. Deut 6.32. M<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>la. 2. Ioh. 10.17. P<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>a. 24.50. Roma. 11. Iob. 9.</note>The 2 Article.</head>
                  <p>
                     <hi>I</hi> Beléeue that theſe three perſons, are of one eſſence and ſubſtance, na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture. Authoritie, power, will, good<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe, wiſdome and eternitie. And that theſe three are but one ſpirituall ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtaunce, eternall, without ende and beginning, true, good, iuſt, mercifull, of ſoueraigne power and wiſdome, ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uing and containing in him ſelfe all goodnes, hauing no neede of any thing.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="3" type="article">
                  <head>The 3. Article.</head>
                  <p>
                     <note place="margin">Deut. 6.30 Math. 4.</note>
                     <hi>I</hi> Beleeue that GOD being ſo one<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly one in eſſence and three in perſon
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:13133:14"/> ought onely to be ſerued, honored,<note place="margin">1. Timo. 1. Apoca. 14.</note> fea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red, loued, adored and inuocated in all our neceſſities, as he which can and wil prouide for them and none other: And therefore I ſay and confeſſe,<note place="margin">Eſay. 55. Iere. 2. Pſalm. 50. Math. 6.7.</note> that I beleeue in one God, that is to ſaye: I acknowledge and receyue him for one onely Lorde, Mayſter and Saui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>our, of whome proceedeth all my good<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe, with whom I can do all things, Without whom I can do nothing.<note place="margin">Iohn. 15. Phil. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>. Pſalm. 91. Gen. 17. Leuit. 26. Deut. 28. Pſa. 37.55. Eſai. 49.99 Math. 6.7. 1. Peter. 5.</note> In him alone I doe truſt and fixe all my harte, hoping that he will take my parte againſt all men: aſſiſting me al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wayes through his holye ſpirite, and deliuering me from all perilles and daungers, through his grace and mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cye without my merits, adminiſtring vnto me all thinges neceſſary, aſwell for the ſoule as body: as a good father, as he promiſed me by his word.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="4" type="article">
                  <head>The .4. Article.</head>
                  <p>
                     <hi>I</hi> Beleeue that he being altogether puiſſant,<note place="margin">Gene. 1. Pſa 33.101</note> hath of nothing from the beginning, created Heauen and Earth, and all things that are therin.
<pb facs="tcp:13133:15"/> That is to ſaye:<note place="margin">Iere. 32. Mala. 2. Iob. 1.2. Lament. 3. Actes. 17. Hebre. 1.</note> all thinges aſwell ce<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſtiall as terreſtriall, viſible as inui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſible, reaſonable as vnreaſonable, ſen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſible as inſenſible: Whome he kée<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peth, guideth, ruleth and gouerneth, through his diuine wiſdome, without whoſe prouidence nothing commeth to paſſe, neyther in this world, nor in the other.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="5" type="article">
                  <head>The .v. Article.</head>
                  <p>
                     <note place="margin">Ge<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>. 1.2.5.9 Ephe. 4. Coloſ. 3. Sapient. 2. Eccle. 17.</note>
                     <hi>I</hi> Beléeue that the ſame God the fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, Sonne and holye Ghoſt, after hauing created all thinges, created and made man, after his owne Image and likeneſſe, that is to ſaye: immor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tall, good, iuſt, true, ſage, wiſe, merci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full and perfit in all thinges, pertici<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pating vnto him his goodneſſe, righte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ouſneſſe and other perfections of God, hauing a will that can accorde and a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>grée in all and by all vnto the will of his Lorde,<note place="margin">Eccle. 15.</note> and that altogether by grace, without any merit.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="6" type="article">
                  <head>The .vi. Article.</head>
                  <pb n="3" facs="tcp:13133:15"/>
                  <p> 
                     <hi>I</hi> Do alſo beléeue that as the Lorde hath created all things celeſtiall and terreſtiall, for the ſeruice of man,<note place="margin">Gene. 1. Pſalm. 19. 1. Cor. 3. Sapien. 13. Roma. 1.</note> &amp; to the ende that by his creatures, he ſhould come vnto the knowledg of the Creator,<note place="margin">Gene. 2.</note> that alſo he hath made &amp; faſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>oned Ma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> for him ſelfe, that of him and by him, he ſhoulde be knowne, loued, feared, ſerued and honored: (this is the ſoueraigne goodneſſe of man) and that in him ſhoulde ſhine the Image of the heauenlye vertues and perfections in al good works,<note place="margin">1. Cor. 6. 1. Theſ. 4.</note> 
                     <note place="margin">Iohn. 17. Ephe. 2. Coloſ. 1. 2. Peter. 2. Iude. 1. Apoca. 12. Math. 25.</note> the which GOD hath prepared that we ſhould walke in the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, vnto his honor and glorye, and to the confuſio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> of the aduerſary, and by that meanes the ruine of the Angels was reſtored and man poſſeſſed the eternal kingdome made and prepared for him before the conſtitution of the worlde.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="7" type="article">
                  <head>The .vii. Article.</head>
                  <p>
                     <hi>I</hi> Beléeue the ſame man to haue byn conſtituted by the Lorde God,<note place="margin">Gene. 1. Pſalm. 8. Gene. 3. Roma. 5. Dani. 7. Mat. 11.2<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>
                     </note> may<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſter and ruler ouer al creatures, the which he did looſe by his ſinne, aſwell for him ſelfe as for all his poſteritie:
<pb facs="tcp:13133:16"/> the which domination and ſegniory,<note place="margin">Iohn. 8.13 Phil. 2.</note> I beléeue nowe to appertaine vnto one onely Ieſus Chriſt very GOD and man, and vnto thoſe to whome he wil beſtow it, as are the faythfull and not vnto the infidels and reprobate.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="8" type="article">
                  <head>The .viii. Article.</head>
                  <p>
                     <note place="margin">Gene. 3. Pſalm. 49.</note>
                     <hi>I</hi> Beleue, the firſt ma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> thorow the ſub<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>tilty and craft of Sathan to be falle<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> from the excellentneſſe, in whiche God created him, agreeing thorow his free wil (which then he had) to the can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teloas ſuggeſtion of the Serpent,<note place="margin">Eccle. 15.</note> wherby he hath loſt the benefits which the Lord gaue vnto him.<note place="margin">Pſ. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>.13.52 Eccle. 17. Oſeas. 13.</note> In ſo much that of wiſe he became fooliſh, of iuſt, vniuſt: of true, a lyer: of perfect, alto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gether vnperfect: hauing afterwarde a will altogether depraued,<note place="margin">Rom. 3.5.7 Phil. 2. 1. Cor. 2 Iohn. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>.15</note> which can not, nor will not agrée with the will of GOD: but altogether vnto the will of the Deuil, the world, the fleſh and of ſinne: not able to do anye thing of him ſelfe, but euill, for that he is altogea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther carnall, captiue, bonde and ſould vnder ſin:<note place="margin">Roma. 7.</note> Beholde the free (or rather)
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:13133:16"/> the bonde will of man for the eſtate of of this preſent lyfe.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="9" type="article">
                  <head>The .ix. Article.</head>
                  <p>
                     <hi>I</hi> Beléeue that that diſcorde and cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ruption of nature,<note place="margin">Gene. 8. Pſ. 14, 140 Eſay. 59. Iohn. 8. Roma. 3.5, 1. Cor. 15.</note> was not onely in <hi>Adam</hi> becauſe of his ſin: but alſo in all men generally which deſcend from him (one onelye Ieſus Chriſt except) inſomuch that they are all according to theyr nature corrupted, vnrighte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous, lyers, ignoraunt,<note place="margin">Iere. 10. Iohn. 15. Roma. 7. 1. Cor. 3. Iohn. 3. Titus. 3.</note> ingratefull and vnperfect altogether: Not being able according to their nature, to do, think, ſpeake nor will any thing which plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeth God, vntyll ſuch time as they are regenerated and renewed by the ſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rite of God.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="10" type="article">
                  <head>The .x. Article.</head>
                  <p>
                     <hi>I</hi> Beléeue that this corruption of na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture (otherwiſe called,<note place="margin">Pſalm. 51. Ephe. 2. Roma. 7. Gene. 2. Iob. 4.5. Iohn. 5. Roma. 5. Roma. 6</note> originall ſin) is the beginning &amp; roote of all other ſins, by which do come vnto vs, all the miſeries, calamities and aduerſities whiche we ſuffer in this lyfe, aſwell in bodye as in ſpirite, and in the ende double death, to wit of body and ſoule.
<pb facs="tcp:13133:17"/> Theſe are the fruites and rewardes for ſinne:<note place="margin">3. Reg. 19. Roma. 11. Iohn. 10. Roma. 8. 1. Timo. 2.</note> But although that the ſame is due and common vnto all men ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nerallye, yet neuertheleſſe the Lorde through his mercye, hath reſerued a certaine number, (to him only know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>en) whome he hath drawne from this corrupted maſſe, &amp; hath ſanctified and clenſed them in the blood of his Sonne Ieſus Chriſt. And by that meanes hath made the veſſels of election to ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nor,<note place="margin">Rama. 9. 1. Timo. 2.</note> apt and fit to all good workes. And therfore.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="11" type="article">
                  <head>The .xi. Article.</head>
                  <p>
                     <note place="margin">Math. 25. Ephe. 1. 2. Timot. 1. Titus. 1.3. Roma. 8. Galath. 4. Eſay. 49. Pſal. 113. Math. 7.</note>
                     <hi>I</hi> Beléeue that the Father in Ieſus Chriſt his Son, by the holy Ghoſt, hath elected and choſen thoſe that be his, according to his good wil, before y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> foundation &amp; conſtitution of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> world, whome he hath predeſtinated to eter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nall lyfe, becauſe they were his Chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren by adoption, hauing greater care of them,<note place="margin">Iob. 1.2.21</note> without any compariſo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, then the beſt Father could haue, of the beſt childe of this world, not ſuffering that any thing ſhould come fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the heauens
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:13133:17"/> aboue, or from the earth beneath,<note place="margin">Pſal. 94.73 Math. 8.1<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>
                     </note> but it ſhoulde be for theyr vtilitye and great profit.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="12" type="article">
                  <head>The .xii. Article.</head>
                  <p>
                     <hi>I</hi> Beléeue that the father by his Son with the holy Ghoſt from the begin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning,<note place="margin">Iere. 31. Ephe. 1.2.3 1. Peter. 1. Gene 1.22. Galath. 3. Deut. 18. Eſay. 40.</note> hath alwaies ſeene to the re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtoring of man, to whom he manifeſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed him ſelfe, yea after the ſinne, ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king vnto him a promiſe of the bleſſed ſeede, by which y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> Serpents head muſt be broken, and the faythfull ought to receyue bleſſing by that promiſe,<note place="margin">Gen. 17.21 2. Reg. 7. Pſal. 132. Luke. 1. Gala 4.</note> (af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terwardes oftentymes confirmed and ratefyed to the holye fathers) the man (otherwiſe in deſpaire in his ſinne) be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing releued, ayded and comforted, hath lyued in hope vnto the exhibiting and accompliſhing of the ſame.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="13" type="article">
                  <head>The xiii. Article.</head>
                  <p>
                     <hi>I</hi> Do alſo beléeue that after this pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſe,<note place="margin">Exod. 19. Leuit. 18. Ezech. 20. Roma. 10. Galath. 3.</note> the Lorde hath preſcribed and geuen the lawe of the commaunde<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mentes to man, promiſing life vnto
<pb facs="tcp:13133:18"/> thoſe that kéepe them, and death vnto thoſe that tranſgreſſe them,<note place="margin">Baru 4.</note> and he ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ueth them not that man ſhoulde ſeeke iuſtification,<note place="margin">Exo. 20.21 22.23. Ezech. 20. 1. Timo. 1,</note> health or lyfe in them: but for the pollicie, peace and tranqui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>litie of his people: for to defende the good, and to chaſtice &amp; correct the wic<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ked, and to houlde and kéepe euery one in his office:<note place="margin">Rom. 3.5.7 1. Cor. 15. Galath. 3.</note> And chiefly y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> by the ſame, man ſhould better know him ſelfe, his diſeaſe, pooreneſſe and imperfection. And by that meanes ſhould haue occa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion to humble him ſelfe before the law geuer, and to ſeeke remedy, health and lyfe, otherwiſe, to wit, in the holy ſeede promiſed, which is Ieſus Chriſt. For that cauſe it is called a Scoole<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mayſter,<note place="margin">Gene 3.17. Deut. 18. Actes. 3. Galath. 3. Rom. 3.5.7 Galath. 3. Iohn. 5. Leuit. 26. Deu. 27.28 Gala 3. 2. Cor. 3. Gene. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>. Math. 27. Luke. 22. Iohn. 18. Galath. 3.</note> for to come vnto Chriſt: the which alſo ſerueth vs as a glaſſe for to knowe our vices, our ſpirituall lepro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſie, and to augment that knowledge. In like manner it ſerueth vs for an accuſer, to accuſe vs before the Lorde: and inſtéede of a ſeuere &amp; cruell Iudge, for to declare the wrath &amp; iudgement of GOD vpon vs, the condemnation and eternal death, &amp; by that meanes to feare vs, and to make vs in diſpayre,
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:13133:18"/> vntyll ſuch tyme as we be comforted by the Goſpel, which is the faith in Ie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſus Chriſt, by y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> which we are exempt and deliuered from all thoſe maledic<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tious. Theſe are the Offices of the lawe, the which are tourned to vs in goodneſſe, by the ſayth of the Goſpell, the which hath oppoſitiue offices and altogether contrary. Furthermore,<note place="margin">Pſalm. 19. Roma. 7. 1. Timo. 1. Hebre. 7. Rom. 1.7.8. Actes. 15.</note> I confeſſe y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> the law of God is good, right, holy and perfect, and wheras it bring<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth nothing to perfection, the faulte is not in it, but in vs: which are altoge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther imperfecte, nor we can not anye thing at all accompliſh it, not to touch it with the leaſt finger: And therfore.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="14" type="article">
                  <head>The .xiiii. Article.</head>
                  <p>
                     <hi>I</hi> Beléeue and confeſſe Ieſus Chriſt to be the fulneſſe,<note place="margin">Rom. 10. Galath. 3. 1. Cor. 1. Math. 5. Roma. 8. Pſa. 18.32. 130 143. Exod. 34. D<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>niel 9. Actes. 15.</note> the ende and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>mation of the lawe, to the righte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ouſneſſe of all beleeuers, to whom &amp; by whom onely, al the promiſes of the fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther are fulfilled, whoe alſo alone hath perfectly ſatiſfied the lawe, the which none among men could do, for ſomuch as the lawe commaundeth impoſſible
<pb facs="tcp:13133:19"/> thinges to the corruptible man, the which neuertheleſſe he ſhall fulfill, not in working:<note place="margin">Rom. 8.11. Galath. 3.</note> but in beleeuing, as alſo y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> lawe is fulfilled by fayth and not by workes, and by that meanes he ſhall finde the righteouſneſſe of fayth auai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lable before the Lorde, and not thoſe of workes,<note place="margin">Rom. 10. Phil. 3. Hebre. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>.</note> the which bringeth nothing vnto perfection.</p>
               </div>
            </div>
            <div type="introduction">
               <p>BEholde as touching the firſt poynt of my faith, what I beleue of the Father &amp; of the thinges made by him, and conſequently of the holy Trinitie, with the fall of man.</p>
               <p>Let vs now come vnto the ſecond point, which is of the Sonne of GOD, and of the things done by h<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>m, chiefly of the reſto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring and reparing of man.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="commentary">
               <head>I beleeue in Ieſus Chriſt his onely Sonne our Lorde, which was conceaued by the holye Ghoſt, borne of the Virgin MARY: ſuffered vnder PONCE PI<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>LATE, was crucified dead &amp; buried, deſcended into Hell: the thirde day he aroſe againe from
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:13133:19"/> death. He aſcended into Heaue<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, there he ſitteth at the right hand of GOD the Father almighty. From thence ſhall he come to iudge the quicke and the deade.</head>
               <div n="15" type="article">
                  <head>The .xv. Article.</head>
                  <p>
                     <seg rend="decorInit">I</seg> Beléeue y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> Ieſus Chriſt is verye God and ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry man,<note place="margin">Eſay. 7.9. Math. 1. Iohn. 1.3. Pſal. 2.110 Roma. 1.9. Heb. 1.2.3. 1. Iohn. 4.5. Hebre. 2.4.</note> hauing two na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures inte<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>mixts in one perſon, y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> diuine nature according to whiche he is the naturall Son of God, equall to the Father in al &amp; through al. And humaine nature, ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to the which he is verye man in all and by al, lyke vnto vs, ſin onely excepted.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="16" type="article">
                  <head>The .xvi. Article.</head>
                  <p>
                     <hi>I</hi> Beléeue that Ieſus Chriſt the Son of GOD in the fulneſſe of tyme prefixed and preordained of the Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther from euerlaſting,<note place="margin">Roma. 8. Galath. 4. Phil. 2. Eſay. 7. Math. 1.</note> was ſent into the world by the Father, &amp; was made
<pb facs="tcp:13133:20"/> very ma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>,<note place="margin">Luke. 1. Galath. 4. Gene. 3.22. 2. Reg. 7. Pſalm. 132</note> conceaued within the womb of a Virgin called <hi>Mary,</hi> of the proper ſubſtaunce and of pure blood purifyed of her: becauſe that he was found very Man, deſcending from the ſéede of <hi>A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dam, Noe, Abraham, Iſaac, Iacob, Da<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uid,</hi> and of the other fathers, to whom the promiſe was made.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="17" type="article">
                  <head>The .xvii. Article.</head>
                  <p>
                     <note place="margin">Math. 1. Luke. 1, Iob. 14. Pſalm. 51.</note>
                     <hi>I</hi> Do alſo beleeue all that to be done by the operation of the holy Ghoſt, without the worke of man, to the ende that all ſhould be holy, vndefiled, pure and cleane, and by that meanes our conception was purified and ſanc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tifyed, the which of it ſelfe was mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red and defyled with ſinne.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="18" type="article">
                  <head>The .xviii. Article.</head>
                  <p>
                     <note place="margin">Math. 1. Luke. 2. Eſay. 7.9. Ezech. 44.</note>
                     <hi>I</hi> Beleeue the ſame Ieſus Chriſt to be borne of the Virgin <hi>Mary,</hi> with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out anye ſin, and without breaking of her virginitie: becauſe that by his pure and holye natiuitie, he purifyeth and ſanctifyeth ours, the which of it
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:13133:20"/> ſelfe is altogether marred and defiled with ſinne.<note place="margin">Iohn. 3. Ephe. 2. Gene. 1.2.3 Math. 9. 1. Tim. 1. Eſay. 9. Iohn. 3. Roma. 8.</note> In that natiuitie of Chriſt I ſee and conſider the firſte eſtate and condition of man: with his fall which was the cauſe of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> comming of Chriſte into this world, likewiſe the grace and beneuolence of GOD the Father: who hath repreſented and geuen vnto vs his onely begotte<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ſonne for to ſerue vs: And the loue of the ſon,<note place="margin">Phil. 2. 2. Cor. 8. Gala. 4. Rome. 8.</note> who hath aba<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed and humbled him ſelf for to eleuate and exalte vs, hath made him ſelfe poore for to enrich vs, and hath him ſelf ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iected for to affranchiſe vs, and he is made the ſonne of man, for to make vs the children of God and poſſeſſors of e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ternall life:<note place="margin">Iohn. 1. Ephe. 5. Iere. 18. Luke 15. Roma. 5.</note> by whoſe comming mans nature was reſtored and made noble, and the man that was loſt, broken and deſtroyed, was rayſed vp againe, &amp; ſet agayne in his firſt place, and hath reco<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uered all that which he loſt throwe ſin and more:<note place="margin">Roma. 8. Coloſ. 2. Ephe. 2. Titus. 3.</note> For by that meanes all the treaſures, graces and benedictions of the Lord are geuen and beſtowed vpon him, and that altogether thorow grace without any merites.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="19" type="article">
                  <pb facs="tcp:13133:21"/>
                  <head>The .xix. Article.</head>
                  <p>
                     <note place="margin">Eſay. 26 Math. 2 Marke. 3. Luke. 8. Iohn. 1. 1. Cor. 4. Galath. 4. Roma. 10. Math. 10.</note>I Do alſo beléeue and knowe by the holy ſcriptures an other conception and natiuitie of Chriſte, which is ſpirituall, the which I ſaye to be of no leſſer dignitie, then the firſt. That is, that euerye faythfull man, ought to conceaue in his hart and minde Ieſus Chriſt, thorow a liuely and true faith, and to bring him foorth thorowe the manifeſt confeſſion of the mouth, as often as néede ſhal require.<note place="margin">S. Auguſt.</note> I eſtéeme that conception and natiuitie to be ſo neceſſarye vnto ſaluation, that if the Virgin <hi>Marye</hi> had not more bleſſedly borne Ieſus Chriſt in her hart &amp; mind, then in her womb, y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> carnal maternity would not haue much profited her. By that meanes we are called,<note place="margin">Pſalm. 27. Math. 12. Iohn. 20.</note> y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> mothers, brethren and ſiſters of Ieſus Chriſt.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="20" type="article">
                  <head>The .xx. Article.</head>
                  <p>
                     <hi>I</hi> Beleeue that the ſame Ieſus Chriſt is verely the Chriſt,<note place="margin">Pſal. 110. Eſay. 61. Mat. 1.16. Luke. 2. Ioh. 1.4.6. Heb. 7.9. Deut. 18. Actes. 3. 1. Reg. 10.16. 3. Reg. 1.19 Leuit. 8. Pſal. 45. Eſai. 61. Luke. 4.</note> that is to ſaye: the Meſſias, the annoynted by the
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:13133:21"/> holy Ghoſt, becauſe that he ſhoulde be the true Kyng, Prophete: and great Prieſt of all the beléeuers, the which was promiſed in the Lawe, of whom alſo haue ſpoken all the Prophetes. This annoynting of Chriſt was not corporall with a materiall and viſible oyle: as the ſame of Kyngs, Prieſtes and Prophets in times paſt: But ſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ritual with an inuiſible oyle, which is the grace &amp; gyftes of the holy Ghoſt, of which he was filled aboue al other,<note place="margin">Pſal. 133. Iohn. 1. Ephe. 4. Actes. 11.</note> inſomuch that that oyntment is deſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cended vnto vs, which haue felt and prooued the ſauour thereof, whereby alſo we beare the name of a Chriſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>an, that is to ſay annoynted.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="21" type="article">
                  <head>The xxi. Article.</head>
                  <p>
                     <hi>I</hi> Beléeue that that Sacrifiſor Ieſus Chriſt,<note place="margin">Heb. 7.9.10</note> not to haue bene Leuiticall or carnall,<note place="margin">Leuit. 1.2.4.7.8. Heb. 10. 1. Iohn. 2.</note> for to offer vp and ſacri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fice, bullocks, kyne, or ſuch like things, as <hi>Aaron</hi> did and al his ſucceſſors: but ſpirituall, (yet neuertheleſſe reall and true) for to offer and ſacrifice him ſelf, that is to ſay: his body and his blood
<pb facs="tcp:13133:22"/> for the remiſſion of the ſinnes of all the worlde,<note place="margin">Dani. 7. Iohn. 19. Luke. 17. Rom. 8.</note> as alſo his kyngdome is not of this carnall worlde, but ſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rituall, the which conſiſteth in the guyding and gouerning of his by his holy ſpirite, ouer whom he raigneth by his word,<note place="margin">1. Cor. 4. 2. Cor. 10.</note> and to the vtter deſtruc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of all his aduerſaries, which are ſinne, death, hell, Satan and all infi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dels, wicked and reprobate, which re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bell againſt the word of the Goſpel.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="22" type="article">
                  <head>The .xxii. Article.</head>
                  <p>
                     <note place="margin">Mat. 5.6.7.24.27. Luke. 21.23 Ioh. 17.19.</note>
                     <hi>I</hi> beléeue that Ieſus Chriſt hath tru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lye exerciſed theſe thrée offices, to wete, Prophet, Kyng, and Prieſt, not onely in this worlde, he being a mortall man as we are:<note place="margin">Rom. 8. Heb. 9. Act. 7.</note> But alſo that he yet doth exerciſe them daily in hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uen before y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> face of his father, where he ſtandeth and appeareth continual<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly for vs, and thereof being taught by his ſpirit, aydeth, maynteyneth, and defendeth thoſe that are his, and ther<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore he is called Prophet,<note place="margin">Gen. 13. Pſal. 110. Heb. 7.</note> Kyng, and high Prieſt after the order of <hi>Mel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chiſedech,</hi> which is eternall, and not
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:13133:22"/> after the order of <hi>Aaron</hi> which ended with the Lawe.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="23" type="article">
                  <head>The .xxiii. Article.</head>
                  <p>
                     <hi>I</hi> Beléeue that the ſame Ieſus Chriſt after that he had preached the Goſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pel in the countrey of <hi>Iudea</hi> &amp; <hi>Ga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lile</hi> by the ſpace of thrée yeres or there abouts,<note place="margin">Math. 4.9. Luke. 4. Ephe. 2. Iohn. 5.6.7.8.9.10.11 12.</note> declaring him ſelfe the natu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rall ſonne of God, aſwel by his mira<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>culous workes, as by the words, and wrytings of the Prophetes,<note place="margin">Math. 26. Mark. 14. Luke. 22. Iohn. 18. Act. 2.4. Mat. 27. Mark. 15. Luke. 23. Iohn. 19.</note> that he hath bene vniuſtly and falſely accu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed by the Prieſtes, who when that they had taken him, in their counſell did vniuſtly condemne him to death, being bounde and chayned, brought hym before Pilate, Prouoſt at that tyme in Ieruſalem, who at the in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtance and requeſt of the ſaid Prieſts, hath vniuſtly and without any cauſe condemned hym to death, the moſt horrible and ignominious that one can thinke or excogitate: That is to be put on the croſſe and to be crucified betwéene two théeues, as though
<pb facs="tcp:13133:23"/> he had bene the prince and captaine of them,<note place="margin">Eſai. 53. Sapi. 2. Gala. 3. Philip. 2.</note> the which he endured and ſuf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fred willingly, and innocently with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out deſeruing it: for otherwiſe he had not ſatiſfied for vs, and his croſſe had profited vs nothing at all.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="24" type="article">
                  <head>The .xxiiii. Article.</head>
                  <p>
                     <hi>I</hi> Beléeue alſo that he beyng on the ſame croſſe,<note place="margin">Luke. 23. Iohn. 19. Pſal. 16.18 Actes. 2.</note> dying and yéelding vp his ſpirit to God his father, that he deſcended into hell, that is to ſay: that he verely felte and experimented the great diſtreſſe and payne of death, with the paynes &amp; flames of hell,<note place="margin">Eſai. 53. 2. Cor. 5. Gala. 3. 1. Pet. 2.</note> that is to ſay, the great furor, ire, and the ſeuere iudgement of God vpon hym, as though he had bene man and halfe damned, inſomuch that he was con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrayned to crye with a loude voyce: My God,<note place="margin">Pſal. 22. Math. 2. Mark. 15.</note> my God, why haſt thou for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſaken me. Beholde ſimplie what I vnderſtand by y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> deſcending of Chriſt into hell. Furthermore, I know that this Article was not at the firſt in the Créede, and that many haue vnder<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtanded and interpreted it otherwyſe,
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:13133:23"/> and haue thought Chriſt verely and in very deede to haue deſcended into hell into the place of the dampned, aleadging the text of Saint <hi>Peter,</hi>
                     <note place="margin">1. Pet. 3.4.</note> the which I confeſſe to be couered and hyd fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> me at this preſent. The Lord graunt vs to open the gate and giue vs entrance into thoſe myſteries.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="25" type="article">
                  <head>The .xxv. Article.</head>
                  <p>
                     <hi>I</hi> Beléeue all that to haue bene done, not for hym which neuer dyd any ſinne,<note place="margin">Eſai. 53. Iohn 8.14. 1. Pet. 2. 1. Iohn. 3. Eſai. 53. Iohn. 3. Rom. 5.6. 2. Cor. 5. Gala. 3. Coloſ. 1. 1. Iohn. 2. Gene. 2. Leuit. 26. Deut. 28. Eze. 18.33. Rom. 5.6. Ephe. 2. Coloſ. 2. 1. Theſ. 5. Hebr. 9.10. 1. Pet. 2.3.</note> in whoſe mouth there was neuer found any fraude nor lying: but for vs poore and miſerable ſinners, whoſe place he helde in the croſſe as a pledge, where he repreſented the per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon of al the ſinners, which euer haue bene, are or ſhalbe vntil the end of the worlde. And becauſe that thoſe haue by their ſinnes deſerued to féele and trye the extreme dolours of death, to be forſaken of God, and of all crea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures, to féele the furor, yre and ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uere iudgement of God vpon them: Chriſt who was their pledge dyd ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiſfie for them in the croſſe, &amp; did feele
<pb facs="tcp:13133:24"/> all that ſame and that to affranchiſe vs &amp; delyuer vs from all theſe paynes from the furor, yre, and iudgement of God, from condemnation and eternal death. Herein I reiect and eſtéeme as fables al the lymbe of the fathers and of litle children, purgatorie and other ſuche follyes, dreames and abuſes, which men inuented and founde out, without the word of God.<note place="margin">Act. 11. Mat. 25. Luke. 16. Math. 7.</note> For I be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>léeue and receaue but two places in the other worlde, to wit, paradiſe for the faythfull &amp; elect with the Angels, and hel for the Infidels and reprobate with the dyuels.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="26" type="article">
                  <head>The .xxvi. Article.</head>
                  <p>
                     <hi>I</hi> Beléeue &amp; conſider that death and paſſion (as alſo al other myſteries) of Ieſus Chriſt,<note place="margin">Math. 14. Actes. 7.12. 1. Pet. 2. Eſai. 53. Iohn. 3. Rom. 5.6.8 2. Cor. 5. Gala. 3. Coloſ. 1. Heb. 2.</note> not onely as tou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ching the hiſtorie as a patrone and ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ample for to imitate and folow, as the ſame of holy men which haue died for the Lordes quarrel: But alſo chiefly touching the cauſe, fruites and vſe of the ſame, thereby to knowe the graui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie &amp; burthen of my ſynnes, the grace
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:13133:24"/> and mercie of the father and the loue of the ſonne,<note place="margin">1. Iohn. 2. 1. Pet. 2.</note> by which we are recon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciled with God, deliuered from the ti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rannie of the deuil, releaſed and reſto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red into the libertie of the ſpirit. That is the glaſſe without ſpot for to make vs know our fylthines:<note place="margin">Iohn. 13. Heb. 9.10. Apoc. 1. Rom. 8. 2. Cor. 5. Gala. 4. 1. Tim. 2. 1. Ioh. 2.</note> The lauer or cleare fountaine, for to waſhe &amp; clenſe vs, and the infinite treaſure for to ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiſfie and content our creditors. Of whom and by whom onely, Gods de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uine iuſtice hath bene fully ſatiſfied, for all the ſynnes of all thoſe which haue bene, are and ſhalbe vntill the end of the world.<note place="margin">Gala. 3. Ephe. 2. Coloſ. 2. Iohn. 14. Rom. 3.5. Ephe. 1. Hebr. 1. Apoc. 1.</note> And therefore I be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>léeue and confeſſe the condemnation of Ieſus Chriſt to be my abſolution: his crucifiyng to be my deliueraunce: his deſcending into hell, to be my aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cending into heauen: his death, to be my lyfe: his blood, to be my waſhyng and purgatorie, by whom onely I am waſhed, purified &amp; made cleane from all my ſinnes, ſo that I neither re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceaue nor beléeue that there is any other purgatorie, neither in this worlde, nor in the worlde to come, by which I may be purged, but the onely
<pb facs="tcp:13133:25"/> blood of Ieſus Chriſt,<note place="margin">Heb. 9.</note> by which all is purged and made cleane for euer.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="27" type="article">
                  <head>The .xxvii. Article.</head>
                  <p>
                     <note place="margin">Apoc. 20. Rom. 6. Coloſ. 3. 2. Tim. 1. Hebr. 2. Eſai. 53. Iohn. 19. Rom. 5.</note>
                     <hi>I</hi> Beléeue that Ieſus Chriſt by the ſacrifice of his body, that he offred vpon the trée of the croſſe, hath de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>faced and deſtroyed ſinne, death and Sathan, with al his kingdome, &amp; hath altogether conſummated and finiſhed the worke of our redemption, &amp; hath ended and aboliſhed all other ſacrifi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces: inſomuch that from hencefoorth we muſt not looke nor ſéeke for any other propiciatorie ſacrifice then this, neither for the lyuing nor for y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> dead. For if we ſinne wyllingly,<note place="margin">Heb. 10.</note> after that we haue receyued the knowledge of the trueth, there remayneth no other ſacrifice for the remiſſion of ſynnes, then this here, by which Chriſt alone, hath conſecrated for euer all thoſe which are ſanctified. And therefore.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="28" type="article">
                  <head>The xxviii. Article.</head>
                  <p>
                     <note place="margin">Mat. 26. Mar. 14. Luke. 22. 1. Cor. 11.</note>
                     <hi>I</hi> Beléeue the holye Supper of the Lord, not to be a ſacrifice: but one<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly a remembrance and commemo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ration
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:13133:25"/> of that holy ſacrifice of Ieſus Chriſt. Therefore,<note place="margin">Iohn. 6. Coloſ. 3.</note> it ought not to be adored and woorſhipped as God, nor Chriſt to be in the ſame: but onely in him ſelfe out of all corruptible ele<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments. In like maner I beleeue and confeſſe, that the papiſticall Maſſe<note place="margin">The Maſſe</note> is an inuention and ordinance of man, a ſacrifice of Antichriſt,<note place="margin">Heb. 10.</note> and a forſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king of the ſacrifice of Ieſus Chriſt, that is to ſay: of his death and paſſion,<note place="margin">Mat. 23.</note> that it is a ſtynking and infectious ſepulchre which couereth and hydeth the merite of the blood of Chriſt. And therefore it ought to be aboliſhed, and the holy Supper of the Lord reſtored and ſet agayne in his fyrſt eſtate.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="29" type="article">
                  <head>The .xxix. Article.</head>
                  <p>
                     <hi>I</hi> Alſo doo beleue that as the Prophet <hi>Ionas</hi>
                     <note place="margin">Ionas. 1.2.</note> was in the Whales bellye (which is a place of corruption) thrée dayes and three nightes,<note place="margin">Mat. 22.</note> with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out being any thyng at all corrupted, from whome he came out the thyrde day, without any hurt, ſafe &amp; ſounde: that euen ſo Ieſus Chriſt after his
<pb facs="tcp:13133:26"/> death,<note place="margin">Mat. 27. Mark. 15. Luke. 23. Iohn. 19.</note> was put into a newe ſepulchre (which is a place of corruption) with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in which he was thrée dayes and thrée nightes, not being touched with any infection,<note place="margin">Pſal. 16.30 Actes. 2.</note> ſtynking or corruption, but alwayes abode ſafe and ſound, for to declare the vertue of his blood, for to accompliſhe the writing of the ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly Prophets,<note place="margin">Eſai. 11.</note> and for to verefie the ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ritie aſwel of his body as of his death, with which I beléeue the lawe to be buryed,<note place="margin">2. Cor. 3. Gala. 4. Ephe. 2. 1. Tim. 1.</note> abrogated, and aboliſhed to the faythfull, not as touching the ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligation that they ſhoulde be no more bounde to lyue and walke after the ſame:<note place="margin">Iohn. 3.8. Rom. 8. 1. Iohn. 3.</note> but onely as touching the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>demnation, that is to ſay, that the tranſgreſſion of the ſame, doeth not condemne them at the iudgement of God, through the faith that they haue in Chriſt. And therefore within one ſepulchre, I comprehend thrée things buryed,<note place="margin">Rom. 6. Gala. 5.6. Coloſ. 3.</note> that is to ſay, Chriſt, the law, and all the faythfull, which ought to be crucified and buryed with Chriſt through the mortification of theyr fleſhe.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="30" type="article">
                  <pb n="13" facs="tcp:13133:26"/>
                  <head>The .xxx. Article.</head>
                  <p>
                     <hi>I</hi> Beléeue that euen as Ieſus Chriſt was delyuered to death for our ſinnes,<note place="margin">Rom. 4.6. 1. Cor. 15. Mat. 28. Iohn. 20. Rom. 1. Iohn. 2. Oſeas. 13. Ioh. 12.16. Luke. 11. Heb. 2.</note> that ſo he aroſe agayne the thirde day for our iuſtification to im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mortall lyfe: wherein hee declared hym ſelfe openly to be very God and very man, triumphing ouer all his e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nemies, hauing confounded and bea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten downe all his enemies, that is to ſay, the worlde, ſinne, death, hell, and Satan: not ſo much for him ſelfe, as for vs which beléeue in him, knowing his victorie to be ours, &amp; that in hym and through him we vanquiſhe thoſe ſame enemies hauyng victorie ouer them, to the honour of God and our great profite.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="31" type="article">
                  <head>The .xxxi. Article.</head>
                  <p>
                     <hi>I</hi> Beléeue &amp; conſider that reſurrecti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of Ieſus Chriſt not only as tou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ching the ſtorie,<note place="margin">Iohn. 11. Mat. 27. Luke. 7.</note> as the ſame of La<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zarus, or other lyke which haue bene miraculoſlye rayſed vp through the
<pb facs="tcp:13133:27"/> vertue and power of the Lord,<note place="margin">Oſe. 6. 1. Cor. 15. Phil. 3. Coloſ. 1. 1. Pet. 1.3.</note> but al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſo as the example and efficient cauſe thereof, as the ſeales and markes of the general reſurrection of al the be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>léeuers: for as Chriſt is rayſed the thirde day after his death, through his diuine vertue, into immortal lyfe: ſo by the vertue of the ſame, I hope to ryſe one day,<note place="margin">1. Theſ. 4.</note> in body and ſoule, into eternall lyfe, afterwards to be here in this world rayſed in ſpirit through a newe and true fayth, in newnes of lyfe,<note place="margin">Rom. 6. Coloſ. 3. Gala. 5.6.</note> mortifying and crucifiyng the fleſhe with the affections and concu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>piſcences of worlde, the which ought to be dead and crucified vnto vs, and we vnto it:<note place="margin">Rom. 6.</note> for we are buryed with Chriſt in his death, by the baptiſme, that as he roſe agayne from death by the glory of the father without euer dying any more: that ſo we ſhoulde walke in newnes of life without euer ſeruing any more ſinne,<note place="margin">Coloſ. 3.</note> ſeekyng al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wayes chiefly the things aboue, cele<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtiall &amp; eternall: Forſaking the earth<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly &amp; tranſitorie thinges of this world, knowyng that we haue not here a continuall Citie:<note place="margin">Hebr. 13.</note> but let vs ſéeke that
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:13133:27"/> which is to come.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="32" type="article">
                  <head>The xxxii. Article.</head>
                  <p>
                     <hi>I</hi> Beléeue alſo and confeſſe,<note place="margin">Mark. 16. Luke. 24. Act. 1. Pſal. 68. Ephe. 4. Iohn. 3.17.</note> that Ie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſus Chriſt the fourty day after his reſurrection, viſibly, and before all his Apoſtles eyes went vp into hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uen, that is to ſay: in the maieſtie of God his father, in glory and eternall felicitie, in which he was before, he came into this miſerable world, for to be made man, yea before the conſtitu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of the world, that is to ſay: from euerlaſting.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="33" type="article">
                  <head>The xxxiii. Article.</head>
                  <p>
                     <hi>I</hi> Beléeue that he aſcended in heauen for to accompliſhe and fulfill,<note place="margin">Ephe. 4. Iohn. 16.</note> and to make an end of his pilgrimage:<note place="margin">Iohn. 14. Heb. 10.</note> al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſo for to prepare vs the place, and to open the way for vs in heauen, that we may there aſcend after hym,<note place="margin">Iohn. 17. Ephe. 12.</note> and folow hym as our head, for to be eter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nally vnited with him in glory. The which we begin here through fayth:<note place="margin">1. Cor. 12. Ephe. 4.</note> in like maner becauſe, that of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſame
<pb facs="tcp:13133:28"/> he beautifieth his Church, in ſending the Comforter vnto his Apoſtles (as hee promiſed them) by which they ſhould be comforted,<note place="margin">Ioh. 14.16. Actes. 1.2.</note> inſtructed, and directed in all trueth: and the Church ſuſteyned, mainteyned, and defended, againſt the wynds of Satan and all the gates of hell.<note place="margin">Mat. 16.</note>
                  </p>
               </div>
               <div n="34" type="article">
                  <head>The .xxxiiii. Article.</head>
                  <p>
                     <note place="margin">Ioh. 14. Rom. 8. Heb. 9.</note>
                     <hi>I</hi> Alſo beléeue that he is aſcended in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to heauen, for to be there our Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trone, Interceſſor, Mediator, and Aduocate, becauſe that nowe he ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peareth for vs, before his fathers face obteyning for vs grace &amp; abundance of all goodnes.<note place="margin">Mat. 11. Actes. 4. 1. Tim. 2. 1. Iohn. 2.</note> In ſo much that I knowe nor receyue any other Medi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ator betwene God and men, nor any other Aduocate, nor Interceſſor be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore GOD the father then his onely ſonne Ieſus Chriſt our Lorde. Vnto him I drawe my ſelfe, of him I con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tent my ſelfe, and any other I wyll not ſéeke nor looke for, fearing to blaſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pheme the name of God, giuing vnto the creature that which belongeth
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:13133:28"/> vnto the Creator, or vnto the ſeruant that which apperteyneth vnto the maiſter.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="35" type="article">
                  <head>The .xxxv. Article.</head>
                  <p>
                     <hi>I</hi> Beléeue that all thoſe which de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maunde, ſearch,<note place="margin">Eſai. 55. Iere. 2. Math. 11. Ioh. 14.16. 1. Tim. 2. 1. Iohn. 3.</note> or receyue any o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther Mediator, Interceſſor, or Ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uocate, towards God the father then Ieſus Chriſt his ſonne, doe abuſe and dreame them ſelues greatly, yea doe blaſpheme againſt God, and doe diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>honour vnto Ieſus Chriſt, and to the Saintes by which they pray.<note place="margin">Mat. 3.11.17. Luke. 3.9. Iohn. 1.3.6. 2. Cor. 4. Coloſ. 1. Heb. 1.</note> For as God the father woulde be knowen, ſerued, loued, feared, and honoured in his ſonne Ieſus Chriſt &amp; not by any other meanes, ſo would he be prayed vnto and called vpon in his ſonne and by the onely name of his ſonne, &amp; not otherwiſe. For beſides Ieſus Chriſt there is no other God. Herein I think not nor will not ſpeake euil of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> bleſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed Saints<note place="margin">The ſaints.</note> which are in heauen with the Lord, but wyl honour and reue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rence them, as lawful &amp; faythfull ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uants of the Lord,<note place="margin">1. Cor. 3.6. Rom. 12. Ephe. 4.5.</note> as the Temple of the holy Ghoſt and true members of
<pb facs="tcp:13133:29"/> Chriſt,<note place="margin">1. Cor. 4.11 Phil. 3. 2. Theſ. 3. Heb. 6.11.15</note> and wyll haue them as myr<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rours and examples before my eyes, for to folowe them aſwel in their good lyfe &amp; conuerſation: as in their fayth and holy doctrine. Furthermore of them or by them, I look for none other thing, knowing that all my goodnes, ayde and helpe, procéedeth from one onely God,<note place="margin">Pſal. 121. Eſai. 45. Iere. 2. Oſeas. 13. Rom. 11. Iam. 1. Coloſ. 1. 2. Theſ. 1.</note> by the meanes of one one<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly Ieſus Chriſt, who hath made the Saintes worthie of his glory by his free grace, by which alſo (as I beleeue) he wyl make me worthie with them for to be their companion in glory, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe that al together doe giue honor, prayſe and glory vnto him alone,<note place="margin">Apoc. 4.19.</note> for euer and euer.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="36" type="article">
                  <head>The .xxxvi. Article.</head>
                  <p>
                     <note place="margin">Pſal. 110. Coloſ. 3. Heb 8.10.12 Mat. 8. Iob. 1.2.21 Pſal. 37.94 Iohn. 1.10. Heb. 1.</note>
                     <hi>I</hi> Beléeue that the ſame Ieſus Chriſt is ſet downe at the ryght hande of God the father almightie. That is to ſay, that he raigneth in one ſelfe maieſtie and equall power with God his father, by whom he ſo gouerneth his vntill the conſummation of the world, that no power of the aduerſary
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:13133:29"/> can hurt them without his permiſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on and wil:<note place="margin">Pſalm. 8. Mat. 11.28 Ioh. 13.17.</note> Alſo the father hath made and conſtituted him Lord and Ruler ouer all creatures, celeſtiall and ter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reſtriall, geuing him all power ouer heauen and earth,<note place="margin">Ephe. 1. Philip. 2. Heb. 2.</note> when he eleuated him aboue all principallitie and po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wer, vertue and ſeignory, and aboue euery name which is named, not one<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lye in this worlde:<note place="margin">Eſai. 42. Rom. 12. 1. Cor. 12. Ephe. 1. Coloſ. 1. Math. 16. Ephe. 5.</note> but alſo in that to come. And hath aſſubiected all thin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ges, vnder his feete: Conſtituting him aboue all thinges to be the head of the Church, the which is his body. And therefore I receiue not nor acknow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge anye other to be the head of the church: but one only Chriſt, who hath geuen his bloud for to waſh her from her filthineſſe, and to heale her of her woundes, who keepeth, nurriſheth,<note place="margin">Iohn. 14.16 Mar. 21. 1. Cor. 3. Ephe. 2. 1. Pet. 2.</note> defendeth and gouerneth her by his ſpirite. He is the only head and foun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dation of the Church, vpon whome e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uery one ought to builde according to his vocation.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="37" type="article">
                  <head>The .xxxvii. Article.</head>
                  <pb facs="tcp:13133:30"/>
                  <p>
                     <note place="margin">Mark. 16. Iohn. 20. Actes. 1.3. Irene. Turtul. S. Ierom. S. Auguſt. Virgil. Flugence.</note>
                     <hi>I</hi> Beléeue that Ieſus Chriſte is aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cended into heauen, and that hee is there corporallye: that is to ſay, in fleſh, bone, body and ſoule. So that he is not, nor cannot be (by ſuch meanes and faſhion) here below on the earth with vs, for aſmuch as his body (al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>though that it be glorious) cannot be in diuerſe places, nor in many places at one very tyme: but ſo in one (accor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding to the nature of his glorious bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy) that then hee cannot be in anye o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther:<note place="margin">Math. 14. Mark. 6. Luke. 24. Iohn. 20.</note> otherwiſe he ſhould not be a true and naturall body, but a ſhadow: that is to ſaye: a thing appearing and not being, the which is falſe, and altoge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther againſt our faith. And therfore I ſay and confeſſe the true and naturall body of Chriſte,<note place="margin">Actes. 3. 1. Cor. 15. Ephe. 1.</note> to be in heauen, and that from thence he ſhall not departe, vntyll he hath put all his enemies vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der his féete, and come for to iudge both the quick and the dead.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="38" type="article">
                  <head>The .xxxviii. Article.</head>
                  <p>
                     <note place="margin">Ma. 24.25. Acts. 3.</note>
                     <hi>I</hi> Beléeue when the number of the e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lect children of God ſhalbe accom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pliſhed,
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:13133:30"/> the Lorde Ieſus in that ſame bodye, with which hee ſuffered,<note place="margin">2. Theſ. 3. Pſal. 50.97 Eſai. 65.66 Dani. 7. Malac. 3. 2. Pet. 3. Iohn. 5. Rom. 2. 2. Tim. 2.</note> with which he roaſe and aſcended into hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uen, ſhall come with great power and maieſtie, viſibly in a clowde, euen as he aſcended, and that ſhalbe to iudge the quick and the dead, and ſhall geue vnto euery one according to Iuſtice, vnto the good which ſhalbe founde a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mong them, after theyr goodneſſe, and to the wicked after their naughtines. That iudgement ſhalbe general:<note place="margin">Eſai. 45. Mat. 24.2<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap> Iohn. 5. Rom. 14. 1. Theſ. 4. 1. Cor. 15.</note> that is to ſay, all ſhalbe called and ſummo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned to appeare perſonally, by y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> voice of the Aungell, to which, all ſhall ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peare, aſwell the good as euyll, the e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lect, as reprobate, that euery one doo make and render vp his accompt and reckoning before the iudiciall ſeate of Chriſte,<note place="margin">2. Cor. 5.</note> of all thinges done by them in this world, be it good or ill: yea,<note place="margin">Math. 12. Dani. 12. Apoc. 20.</note> for euery idle worde, the which the world doth not thinke to be ſin. Then ſhall all thoſe be ſaued, which ſhalbe found written in the booke of lyfe.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="39" type="article">
                  <head>The .xxxix. Article.</head>
                  <pb facs="tcp:13133:31"/>
                  <p>
                     <note place="margin">Mat. 25. Mark. 4. Math. 13.</note>
                     <hi>I</hi> Beleeue that then ſhalbe made the totall and laſt ſeperation of the good from the wicked, of the elect from the reprobate, the which nowe are mingled together, as the good fiſhes and badde in the nettes, the chaffe with the corne, and the darnell with the wheate:<note place="margin">Math. 5. Luke. 3.</note> But when the harueſt commeth, he which hath the fanne in his handes will make the ſeperation, and wil put the corne aſide in his gar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner: but the chaf and tares ſhalbe caſt into the fyre, for to burne eternally. Then ſhalbe perfectlye declared and knowen the iuſtice and mercy of the Lorde,<note place="margin">Math. 25. Rom. 2.16. 1. Cor. 4. 2. Theſ. 3.</note> with the fruite of the Croſſe and blood of Ieſus Chriſte: the which now wee know onely but in parte. Then the good and elect ſhal know the ſtone,<note place="margin">2. Pet. 3. Pſal. 118. Eſai. 28. Math. 21. Luke. 2. Actes. 4. 1. Peter. 2.</note> vpon which they builded theyr fayth and hope, and ſhall not be con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>founded: And the wicked ſhall alſo knowe the ſtone, vpon which they ſtumbled, the which they reiected, co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                     <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>temned and deſpiſed, and ſhalbe con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>founded. Then the Lorde Ieſus ſhall make an ende of his office and miniſtrie,<note place="margin">Sopho. 3. 1. Cor. 15. Ephe. 4.</note> for his miſtical body ſhalbe
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:13133:31"/> altogether accompliſhed with all his members, and ſhall render the king<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome and his ſpowſe (which is the Church) vnto God his father, al faire,<note place="margin">Ephe. 5.</note> glorious, erreprehenſible and accep<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>table, without ſpot or wrinckle, or a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny ſuch thing.<note place="margin">1. Cor. 15. Heb. 2.</note> Then ſhalbe perfectly vanquiſhed and confounded Sathan, hell, ſinne and death, and all the other aduerſaries of Chriſte, whoe at this preſent do exerciſe yet tirrany ouer all his members,<note place="margin">Rom. 8.</note> holding them vnder their griefes, bondes and ſnares: But then wee as people rauiſhed for Ioy,<note place="margin">Oſeas. 13. 1. Cor. 15. 1. Ioh. 5.</note> will reherſe the words that are writ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten, O Death where is thy ſtinge? O Hel where is thy victory? But thanks be vnto GOD, which hath geuen vs victorye through Ieſus Chriſte our Lorde.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="40" type="article">
                  <head>The xl. Article.</head>
                  <p>
                     <hi>I</hi> Beléeue that that Iudgement be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing meruelous,<note place="margin">Ioel. 2. Heb. 10. Math. 24. Luke 21. Roma. 8.</note> terrible and feare<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful vnto the wicked and reprobate, is much to be deſired, and of great conſolation vnto the good, faythfull
<pb facs="tcp:13133:32"/> and elect, for aſmuch as the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> their total redemption (to wéete of body) ſhalbe ended,<note place="margin">Pſal. 127. Mat. 25. Luke. 14. Sapience. 5 Exo. 32. Mat. 10.</note> and that they ſhall receiue the fruit of their labors: Their Innocen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cie ſhalbe openly declared and known of all the worlde, and they ſhall ſée the vengaunce and condemnation of the wicked, which haue tirrannouſly af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>flicted and tormented them in this world,<note place="margin">Rom. 2. 1. Cor. 4.</note> whoſe iniquitye and wicked<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe ſhalbe manifeſted by the Lorde, and cleerely knowen of all, to theyr great confuſion, and to the honor and glory of the iuſt children of God, the which ſhalbe in perfect peace and tra<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                     <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quillitie,<note place="margin">Sapience. 5 Eſai. 25.66 Apoc. 7.21.</note> and ſhall haue full ioye and fruition of all that, which the Lorde hath promiſed and prepared for them that loue him.<note place="margin">Eſai. 64. 1. Cor. 2. 1. Iohn. 3.</note> Which the eye hath not ſéene, nor the eare hath heard, nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther hath it entered into mans harte. Therefore I tarry and looke for that great day of retribution,<note place="margin">Rom. 8. 1. Cor. 5.</note> with a great deſire, as the ſame which bringeth and declareth vnto me my chiefeſt goodneſſe.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="41" type="article">
                  <head>The .xli. Article.</head>
                  <pb n="20" facs="tcp:13133:32"/>
                  <p>
                     <hi>I</hi> Beléeue that wee ſhall not all dye,<note place="margin">1. Cor. 15. 1. Theſ. 4. S. Auguſt,</note> but we ſhalbe all changed in a mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment: that is to ſay, that in that lat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter day and general iudgement, ſome ſhalbe found lyuing, which ſhal neuer dye by ſeperation of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> body and ſoule: but ſhall abide ſo alyue eternally, that Chriſte maye be knowen Lorde and Iudge of the quick and the dead,<note place="margin">Dan. 7. 1. Pet. 4. Iohn. 5. Act. 10. Rom. 14. 2. Tim. 4. Rom. 5. Gala. 3.</note> and his grace and merite may be founde greater then the ſinne of <hi>Adam.</hi> For as ſin hath raigned to death: In like-maner muſt grace raign through Ie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſus Chriſt to eternall lyfe. Neuerthe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſſe they ſhalbe chaunged and tranſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formed from corruption into incor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ruption, from mortallity to immor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tallity, from deſpiſing into glory: in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſomuch that they ſhalbe the chiefeſt of of all the giftes, graces and benefites which the Lorde ſhall geue vnto thoſe which before were dead, whome they ſhall not go before:<note place="margin">1. Theſ. 4.</note> but all together ſhalbe rauiſhed in the clowdes before in the ayre, and alſo they ſhall be al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wayes together with the Lorde.</p>
               </div>
            </div>
            <div type="introduction">
               <pb facs="tcp:13133:33"/>
               <p>BEholde for the ſeconde point of my faith, touching Ieſus Chriſte, the ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cond perſon of the Trinitie, and of the reſtoration and repairing of man, don by him.</p>
               <p>Let vs now come vnto the third point, which is of the holie Ghoſte, by whome man is reſtored, maintained and keept in his being.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="commentary">
               <head>I beleeue in the holy Ghoſte.</head>
               <div n="42" type="article">
                  <head>The .xlii. Article.</head>
                  <p>
                     <note place="margin">Gene. 1.6 Pſa. 51.143 Eſa. 59 63. Math. 3.28 Iohn 14.16 1. Iohn. 5. 1. Cor. 12.</note>
                     <seg rend="decorInit">I</seg> Beléeue that the holy Ghoſt, is one diuine perſo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> diſtinct from the father and the ſon pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>céeding of them both, equall in all &amp; thorow all, and coeter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nall with them, by whom the Church hath byn alwayes, is yet and ſhalbe ruled, conducted, direct<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>d and gouer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned, vntill the conſumation of this world: by whome alſo haue ſpoken al the holy Patriarkes, Prophetes and
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:13133:33"/> Apoſtles of our Lorde Ieſus Chriſte. Therefore I beléeue nor receiue any other Vicar or Lieuetenant of Chriſt in earth, within his Church:<note place="margin">Iohn. 14.</note> but the holy Ghoſt, which cannot be receiued of the wicked.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="43" type="article">
                  <head>The .xliii. Article.</head>
                  <p>
                     <hi>I</hi> Beléeue that the holy Ghoſt,<note place="margin">1. Cor. 1.5. Ephe. 1.<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap> Iohn. 1.3. Rom. 8. Gala. 4.</note> is the wages and erneſt of our celeſtiall enheritance, by whom we are aſſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red, aſſertained and liuely perſwaded in our conſciences, that wee are the children of God, and adoptiue brethre<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> of Ieſus Chriſte,<note place="margin">Exo. 8.31. Luke. 11. Iohn. 1<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>. Actes. 2. Rom. 5. 1. Cor. 2. 2. Cor. 1.</note> and conſequentlye Coheyres of eternall lyfe. That is al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſo the finger of God, the which prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teth in our mindes the fayth of thoſe thinges, ſealeth and confirmeth the promiſes of the Lorde within our hartes, through his goodneſſe and grace, that we néede not to doubt any thing at all.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="44" type="article">
                  <head>The .xliiii. Article.</head>
                  <p>
                     <hi>I</hi> Beléeue that that holy Ghoſt,<note place="margin">1. Reg. 10. Pſal. 104.</note> dwel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling in vs, doth regenerate vs tho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>row
<pb facs="tcp:13133:34"/> his grace and vertue,<note place="margin">Iohn. 3. Rom. 6.8. Ephe. 4. Coloſ. 3. Titus. 3.</note> into a re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nouation and chaunging of life, mor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tifiyng in vs, all that which is of vs and of the olde man, the fleſh and the world, and quickning all that which is his, that wee ſhould liue no more to our ſelues: but to Chriſte, who alſo doth and worketh in vs al good works agréeable to the father,<note place="margin">Eſai. 26. Prouer. 16. 2. Cor. 3. Phil. 2. Iohn. 16.</note> and rebuketh, checketh and vanquiſheth the world of ſinne, righteouſneſſe and iudge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="45" type="article">
                  <head>The .xlv. Article.</head>
                  <p>
                     <note place="margin">Math. 10. Luk. 12.21. Iohn. 14. 1. Cor. 2. 1. Iohn. 2. Eſai. 51.66 Iob. 1.2. Iohn. 14. Actes. 6. Rom. 8. 2. Cor. 1.</note>
                     <hi>I</hi> Beleeue that the holy Ghoſt is the Doctor of the Ignorant, who tea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cheth, directeth and leadeth vs into the knowledg of the trueth, by which we are deliuered from darkneſſe and ſet into life. Alſo he is the comforter of the poore afflicted: for to ayde, fortifie, comfort and aſſiſt them in al troubles and aduerſities, that they ſhoulde not diſpaire in them, as the wicked and reprobate doo: but that they ſhoulde taſte and féele,<note place="margin">Acte. 14. Heb. 12. 1. Pet. 14.</note> the gentleneſſe, benig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nitie and mercifulneſſe of the father,
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:13133:34"/> who thorow croſſe and diuerſe trybu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lations doth bring his into eternall glory.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="46" type="article">
                  <head>The .xlvi. Article.</head>
                  <p>
                     <hi>I</hi> Beléeue that that holy Ghoſt,<note place="margin">Gene. 2. Act. 17. Eſai. 57. Iohn. 7.20. Rom. 8.</note> is the ſpirite of lyfe, quickening all other ſpirites, aſwell celeſtiall as terreſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>triall, and that he is only holy in him ſelfe, by whome all other are ſanctifi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed: ſo that, if any ſpirites are holy (as they are) either in heauen or in earth, it is not but thorow the ſanctitie of that holy ſpirite,<note place="margin">Exo. 31. Iere. 1. Eze. 20.3<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap> Iohn. 17. 1. Theſ. 5. Heb. 9.</note> which is the cauſe wherfore I beléeue in him: that is to ſay, that in him I hope and put al my affiance, aſſurance and truſte, as I haue ſpoken before of the Father and the Sonne.</p>
               </div>
            </div>
            <div type="introduction">
               <p>Behold the third point of my faith, which is touching the holie Ghoſt the thirde perſo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> of the holy Trinitie, by whom (after that we are made by the father and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtored by the ſonne) we are kept and go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerned vnto the ende. Now it remaineth
<pb facs="tcp:13133:35"/> to intreat of the fourth point of my faith, which is touching the Church and the thinges concerning the ſame.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="commentary">
               <head>I beleeue the holye catholike Church, the Communion of Saintes.</head>
               <div n="47" type="article">
                  <head>The .xlvii. Article.</head>
                  <p>
                     <note place="margin">Gal. 4. Numb. 20. 1. Cor. 12.14 Ephe. 5. Iohn. 10. Heb. 12. Roma. 8. Ephe. 1. 2. Timo. 1. Titus. 1.3.</note>I Beléeue and confeſſe one one<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lye catholike and vniuerſall Church, which is a holy Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gregation and aſſembly of all the faythfull beléeuers, choſen and predeſtinated to eternall life, before the conſtitutio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> of the world: of whoſe number I accompte and beléeue my ſelfe to be one, thorow the only grace and mercy of the Father, hauing the merite of my good Lorde and Maiſter Ieſus Chriſte, and not by my good workes or merites, which are none at all.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="48" type="article">
                  <pb n="23" facs="tcp:13133:35"/>
                  <head>The .xlviii. Article.</head>
                  <p>
                     <hi>I</hi> Beléeue that Church to be inuiſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble to mans ſight,<note place="margin">1. Reg. 19. Rom. 11. 2. Tim. 2. Gene. 22. Pſal. 2.86. Eſai. 21.49 Iere. 3. Ephe. 4.</note> and vnto God a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lone knowen, the which is not ſet, tyed, or limited in a certaine place, or to certaine men, but diſperſed and ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perated abroad thorow out the world: Neuertheleſſe ioygned together in harte, wil and minde thorow the band of fayth and loue, acknowledging all of them one onely God,<note place="margin">1. Cor. 10.11</note> one only head and mediator Ieſus Chriſt, one faith, one law, one baptiſme, one ſpirituall table, in which one onely meate and one onely ſpirituall drinke is admi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſtred vnto them, vntil the conſuma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of this world.<note place="margin">Math. 23. Iohn. 10. Heb. 11.</note> That Church com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prehendeth in it all the iuſt and elect, from the firſt iuſt <hi>Abell</hi> vnto the laſt, which ſhalbe <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ound in the ende of the world,<note place="margin">Math. 23.</note> and therfore I call it vniuer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſall. For touching the viſible Church, which is the congregation of the good and of the wicked, the elect and repro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bate,<note place="margin">Rom. 10. Hebr. 11.</note> and generally of all thoſe which ſay that they beléeue in Chriſte, I be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>léeue
<pb facs="tcp:13133:36"/> it not, becauſe I ſee it with my eye, and fayth is of inuiſible thinges.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="49" type="article">
                  <head>The .xlix. Article.</head>
                  <p>
                     <note place="margin">Eſai. 2.4.5. Mat. 13.21 1 Tim. 3. 2. Theſ. 2. Heb. 3.</note>
                     <hi>I</hi> Beléeue that that inuiſible Church is the Lordes fielde, within which there is neither cockle nor darnell: but that it is the houſe and habitacle of the holy Ghoſt, within which there is neither <hi>Caim, Iudas,</hi> nor the wicked rich man.<note place="margin">Iohn. 10. Math. 25. Ezec. 34. Zach. 10.</note> That it is alſo the ſheepe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>folde of Chriſte, within which there commeth no ſtincking nor infected goates: but all ſhéepe, lambes and do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>meſticall ewes, bearing fruit in theyr tymes and ſeaſons.<note place="margin">Rom. 12. 1. Cor. 12. Ephe. 4. Pſal. 45. Cant. 2.4. Ephe. 5.</note> That it is the bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy of Chriſt, in which theyr is no rot<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten or corrupt member. That is alſo the ſpowſe of Chriſt, pure and cleane, without ſpot or wrincle or anye ſuch like thing, holy and erreprehenſible, purified and ſanctified in the bloud, and by the word of his head and wel-beloued ſpowſe Ieſus Chriſte,<note place="margin">Iohn. 10. Roma. 8.</note> wher<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore thoſe which are grafted in her through liuely fayth cannot periſh.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="50" type="article">
                  <pb n="24" facs="tcp:13133:36"/>
                  <head>The .l. Article.</head>
                  <p>
                     <hi>I</hi> Beléeue that the giftes and graces of the holy Ghoſt,<note place="margin">Rom. 12. 1. Cor. 12. Ephe. 4.</note> are diſperſed and geuen vnto euery one of the mem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bers of that Church, not ſo much for the perticuler profit &amp; vtility of them, as for the generall profit and vtilitye of al the aſſemble, or Church,<note place="margin">1. Cor. 14. Ephe. 2. Titus. 3.</note> and that altogether through grace, without a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny merite, according to the good will and prouidence of God, to ſome more,<note place="margin">Math. 25. Luke. 19. Rom. 12.15 1. Cor. 12. Coloſ. 2. Gala. 6.</note> and to ſome leſſe, that we may know the one to haue néede of the other, and maye ayde and helpe the one the o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, in all neceſſities, aſwell corpo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rall as ſpirituall, as members of one body.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="51" type="article">
                  <head>The .li. Article.</head>
                  <p>
                     <hi>I</hi> Beléeue the communion of Sain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tes: that is to ſaye,<note place="margin">Math. 25. Ephe. 4. Rom. 12. 1. Cor. 12.</note> that all that whiche the Lorde geueth vs in this worlde, whether they bee goodes concerning the body of the ſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rite, that he geueth them chiefly to the profit and vtillitie of all the Church,
<pb facs="tcp:13133:37"/> and therfore ought to be diſtributed and beſtowed vnto all the faythfull,<note place="margin">Math. 5. Acts. 4. 1. Pet. 4. 1. Iohn. 3.</note> chiefly in neceſſity: Inſomuch, that as we do al communicate in one GOD, in one fayth,<note place="margin">Ephe. 4. 1. Cor. 11.</note> in one law, in one bap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiſme, and in one ſpiritual table, that alſo we may communicate in all that which proceedeth and commeth vnto vs by the meanes of all thoſe things:<note place="margin">Math. 25. 1. Cor. 4. Iames. 5.</note> for otherwiſe we are not Chriſtians, nor faythfull diſpenſators of Chriſte: I alwaies reiect the Anabaptiſticall Communalty of goodes, wiues and o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther like things,<note place="margin">Math. 14. Iohn. 12.13 Acts. 2.4.</note> receiuing the Apoſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>olicall communaltie, which hauing and poſſeſſing ſome goodes perticu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lerly, deuideth and diſtributeth vnto euery one, as he ſhall haue neede, and as neceſſity requireth.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="52" type="article">
                  <head>The lii. Article</head>
                  <p>
                     <hi>I</hi> Beléeue that that Church is as the Arke of <hi>Noe,</hi> within which there was health and lyfe, and out of which there was but death, ruine and per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dition. For as Chriſt is, and raigneth in his Church: ſo Sathan is and raig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neth
<pb n="25" facs="tcp:13133:37"/> altogether out of the ſame,<note place="margin">Math. 28. Iohn. 14. Pſal. 119. Mat. 8.14. Mark. 4. Luke. 8.</note> the which alſo is kept thorow the ſpirite of Chriſte, directed and guided by his worde, and nurriſhed by the Sacra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mentes. She ſhall haue alwayes ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerſaries,<note place="margin">Eſai. 59.63 Zach. 7. Math. 16.</note> and ſhalbe alwaies torme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                     <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted in that ſea, by the thunders of An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>techriſte, and by the windes and tem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peſtes of Sathan.<note place="margin">Eſay. 40.</note> For all the gates of Hell do arme and ſet themſelues a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt it.<note place="margin">1. Cor. 3. Ephe. 2. 1. Iohn. 2. Eſai. 25. Apoc. 19.</note> But ſhe ſhal not be drowned in the waters, but ſhall abyde eter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nally: For ſomuch as ſhe hath a good Patron and foundation, which is Ie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſus Chriſte the righteous. Therfore I call it myllitant, looking for the tri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>umphant of the bleſſed, where there ſhalbe but peace, i<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ie and eternall ſal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uation.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="53" type="article">
                  <head>The .liii. Article</head>
                  <p>
                     <hi>I</hi> Beléeue that the Lorde hath geuen vnto vs three ſignes or principall markes,<note place="margin">Math. 28. Mark. 16. Iohn. 8.10.</note> by which we may knowe that Church, that is to ſay: the word,<note place="margin">2. Pet. 1. Iohn. 5.</note> the Sacramentes, and the diſciplyne. I call the word, onely that which was
<pb facs="tcp:13133:38"/> reuealed by the holy Ghoſt; vnto the holye Patriarkes, Prophetes, and A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſtles of Ieſus Chriſte, the which is contained in the cononicall bookes of the olde and new teſtament,<note place="margin">Iohn. 15. Ioh. 1.3.6.</note> by which we are mundified and receiue the ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry ſame, and altogether aſmuch as by the Sacraments: That is to ſay, that Ieſus Chriſte geueth and communi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cateth himſelfe vnto vs by the word of faith,<note place="margin">Rom. 12. Ephe. 3.</note> aſwell (without ſaying better) as by the Sacraments, although it be after another manner and faſhion.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="54" type="article">
                  <head>The .liiii. Article.</head>
                  <p>
                     <note place="margin">Iohn. 5. Gala. 1. 2. Tim. 3. Eſai. 28. Deut. 4.12.28. Pro. 30. Apoc. 22.</note>
                     <hi>I</hi> Beléeue that word of God to be of more greater authoritie then the Church, the which alone ſufficient<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly declareth and teacheth vnto vs all thinges concerning our ſaluation, what we muſt doo or not doo. That is the true patron, and perfect rule, after which al the faithful ought to gouern and direct their life, without declining either to the right hand or left, with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out chainging anye thing or dimini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhing,<note place="margin">Gene. 1. Deut. 31. Eccle. 1.</note> knowing that all the workes of
<pb n="26" facs="tcp:13133:38"/> God are perfect, and chiefly his word.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="55" type="article">
                  <head>The lv. Article.</head>
                  <p>
                     <hi>I</hi> Beléeue that as one onely Ieſus Chriſt amongſt al men is holy and true,<note place="margin">Eſai. 53. Iohn. 8. 1. Pet. 2. Pſal. 16. Iohn. 8.14.17. Rom. 3. 2 Cor. 1. Eſa. 12.40 55. Iohn. 7. Exo. 13. Pſal. 119. Deut. 8. Math. 4. Iohn. 6. Rom. 1. Phil. 1. 2. Timo. 4.</note> and all other are ſinners and lyers, that alſo amongſt al doctrines, his onelye doctrine is holye and true, and all other are vncleane, and full of lyinges. That doctrine is the foun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taine of life, the lampe and pyller of fyre, for to guide vs: The bread of the ſoule, and the vertue of GOD, to the ſaluation of all beléeuers. Therefore the ſame onely for all occaſion ought to be aduaunced, preached, heard, vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derſtanded, and receiued thorow out the whole worlde: to the conſolation and health of the beléeuers, and to the greateſt condempnation of the vnbe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leeuers, wicked and reprobate.<note place="margin">Exo. 16. Mat. 21. Luke. 2. Iohn. 9. 1. Pet. 2.</note> For as the Manna in the wilderneſſe gaue vn<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>to ſome wormes, and to other ſome good meate, and Chriſte was ſet and geuen as a ſtone of offence, to the ru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ine of the wicked, and reſurrection of the good: So the word of the Goſpell,
<pb facs="tcp:13133:39"/> is vnto ſome a ſauor of death in death and vnto other a ſauor of lyfe in lyfe,<note place="margin">Cor. 2.</note> the which onely I receiue and take,<note place="margin">
                        <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap> Ioſua. 1.</note> for my guide, after which I will liue and dye.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="56" type="article">
                  <head>The .lvi. Article.</head>
                  <p>
                     <note place="margin">Leuit. 19. Deut. 11. Iohn. 5.</note>
                     <hi>I</hi> Beléeue y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> the reading of that word or Goſpell, ought not nor can not be forbidden or prohibited anye man whatſoeuer, of what eſtate or co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>dition ſoeuer he be:<note place="margin">Ma. 24.28. Mark. 6.16 Actes. 1.</note> But ought to be commo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> vnto all the world, aſwell men as wo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>me<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>: yea alſo in a vulgar &amp; co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>mon lan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guag vnderſta<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d of al, for aſmuch as to al generally it is directed, &amp; the promi<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſes of the Lord contained in the ſame appertaineth vnto all,<note place="margin">Roma. 13. Luke. 24.</note> whereby An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>techriſt with all his do exerciſe great and cruell tiranny vpon all the faith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full children of God,<note place="margin">1. Timo. 4. 2. Timo. 3. 2. Pet. 3.</note> aſwell for that he taketh from them and forbiddeth them the reading thereof, ſetting be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore them his dreames, cannons, and damnable traditions in ſtéede of the ſame. But alſo for that he forbiddeth and commaundeth in any indifferent
<pb n="27" facs="tcp:13133:39"/> things, vpon paine of deadly ſin and eternall condempnation, which is a true note and marke of Antechriſt.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="57" type="article">
                  <head>The .lvii. Article.</head>
                  <p>
                     <hi>I</hi> Beléeue that holy euangelical doc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trine,<note place="margin">Heb. 2. Ioh. 5.10. Math. 8.9.10.27. Luke. 9.10. Ac. 3.4.5.9 13.14.19.20</note> to haue byn confirmed in his time by diuine miracles, aſwell by Ieſus Chriſt, the prophets &amp; Apoſtls, as by other faythfull and good mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſters of the ſame: So that it is not neede now to haue, or demau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d other: but to content our ſelues with that which hath byn made, and to beléeue ſimply in the onely worde, without ſéeking any further. Watching and alwayes taking héede that we be not deceiued by the falſe myracles of An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>techriſte (of which the worlde is at this daye full) whiche are doon and wrought by the opperation of ſathan for to conforme all idolatries, errors,<note place="margin">Math. 24. Mark. 13.</note> 
                     <note place="margin">2. Theſ. 2. Apo. 13.16.</note> abuſes and iniquities, in blinding the poore ignoraunt people. The Lorde doth permit the ſame iuſtlye,<note place="margin">3. Reg. 23. 2. Theſſ. 2.</note> becauſe they well not receiue the ſpirite of trueth for to be ſaued. He permitteth
<pb facs="tcp:13133:40"/> that they ſhould receiue the ſpirite of lyinges with the effecacie of abuſion for to be condempned, for that they haue allowed lying and iniquitie. And haue reiected righteouſneſſe and trueth.<note place="margin">Math. 27. Mark. 16. Ioh. 10.21. Act. 3.5.19. 1. Cor. 12. 1. Cor. 14.</note> Then the true myracles are done by the onely vertue of God, for the confirmation of his doctrine, and are geuen vnto the Infidelles, and not vnto the beleeuers: but the pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pheſie, that is to ſaye, the worde is geuen vnto the faythfull and belée<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uers.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="58" type="article">
                  <head>The .lviii. Article.</head>
                  <p>
                     <note place="margin">Gene. 17. Roma. 4. Math. 28. Mark. 16. Luk. 3.</note>
                     <hi>I</hi> Do alſo beléeue the holy Sacra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments (which are the ſecond mark of the true Church (to be the ſignes of the Alliance made betwéene God and vs, by Ieſus Chriſt, ſeales of the Lordes promiſe and externe and vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſible Symboles of the inwarde faith,<note place="margin">S. Auguſt</note> the which are onely two in number: to weete.<note place="margin">Luk. 22. Iohn. 1.3. Titus. 3. Act. 19.</note> Baptiſme, and the holye Supper of the Lorde: Theſe are not voyde and emptye ſignes, but full:
<pb n="28" facs="tcp:13133:40"/> That is to ſaye, not onely ſignifica<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiue ſignes, but alſo exhibitiue, of the thinge they ſignify indeede (as wee wyll declare hereafter GOD wylling.) Touching the other fyue, whiche are receaued and exerciſed with great abuſe and ſuperſtition in the papiſticall Church: to wéete,<note place="margin">Math. 19. 1. Tim. 5. 2. Timo. 1. Mark. 8. Ieam. 5.</note> Confyrmation, Confeſſion, Mary<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>age, laying on of handes, otherwiſe called, order and vnction. I ſaye all thoſe to haue beene eccleſiaſticall ce<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>remonies, whiche the holy Fathers, haue vſed in their tyme holyly, with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out anye ſuperſtition, whiche alſo we may at this daye vſe after theyr example,<note place="margin">2. Cor. 3. Gala. 3.4. Ephe. 2. Coloſſ. 2. Hebr. 9.10.</note> ſo that it be doon without error, abuſe and ſuperſtition: Al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wayes ſaued the chriſtian and euan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gellicall lybertye, the whiche de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lyuereth our conſciences from all externall Ceremonies inſtituted by menne, wythout the woorde of God.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="59" type="article">
                  <head>The .lix. Article.</head>
                  <pb facs="tcp:13133:41"/>
                  <p>
                     <note place="margin">Mat. 28. Mark. 16. Gene. 17. Coloſſ. 2.</note>
                     <hi>I</hi> Beléeue that the Baptiſme, is the ſigne of the new alliance betwéene god and vs, made by Ieſus Chriſt, and the marke of the Chriſtians in the Goſpell, as of late the Circumci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion was the mark of the Iewes vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der the law.<note place="margin">Iohn. 3. Ephe. 5. Titus. 3.</note> That it is alſo an exteri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>or waſhing doon by water, ſignifi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing an interior waſhing in the ſpirit, don by the blood of Chriſte: the which ought to be geuen and beſtowed,<note place="margin">Mat. 19.28 Mar. 10.16 Heb. 6. Ephe. 4.</note> aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>well to the litle Children, as to the olde ones, according to the ordinance of Ieſus Chriſte, and that once only, without reiterating it.<note place="margin">Exo. 14.</note> That is the red Sea, within which, <hi>Pharao</hi> (that is to ſaye the Diuell) with his pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uokementes of ſinne,<note place="margin">1. Cor. 10.</note> is altogether drowned, and the Iſraelites paſſed thorow the middes ſafe.<note place="margin">Acts. 4.</note> And after<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wardes walked thorow the wilder<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe of this worlde, with great an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guiſh,<note place="margin">Iohn. 6.</note> weryneſſe and troubles, vſed daylye the celeſtiall Manna, which is the holye worde of the Lorde, vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tyll they entred by death, into the Lande of the celeſtiall promiſe.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="60" type="article">
                  <pb n="29" facs="tcp:13133:41"/>
                  <head>The lx. Article.</head>
                  <p>
                     <hi>I</hi> Beléeue alſo that the Baptiſme is the entrance of the Church,<note place="margin">Acts. 2. Iohn. 3. Ephe. 5. Titus. 3.</note> a waſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing of regeneration and a renewing in the holye Ghoſt, by which we re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nownce our ſelues, Sathan, the fleſh, ſinne and the worlde,<note place="margin">Rom. 13. Ephe. 4. C<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>lo. 3.</note> for hauing layd away the olde man with all his con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cupicences, we put on the newe man, which is Ieſus Chriſte in righteouſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe and holineſſe,<note place="margin">Rom. 6. Colo. 2. Gala. 3. 2. Cor. 5. Colo. 3.</note> with whome we dye, and are buried in his death, that as Chriſte is ryſen from death, by the glorye of the Father: ſo ſhould we walke in newneſſe of life, mortifiyng alwayes that which is of vs in vs, for to deſtroy and roote out the body of ſinne.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="61" type="article">
                  <head>The .lxi. Article.</head>
                  <p>
                     <hi>I</hi> Beléeue that that baptiſme ought to be adminiſtred (not with oyle,<note place="margin">Mat. 3.28. Mark. 1. Luk. 3. Iohn. 1.3. Act. 13.8.9</note> ſalt, ſpittle, or ſuch like things) but only in pure and cleane water, in the name of the Father, the ſonne and of
<pb facs="tcp:13133:42"/> the holye Ghoſte: after the ordi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nance and inſtitution of God, with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out chaunging any thing, adding or diminiſhing, and that altogether in a vulgare and common language, vnderſtanded of all: foraſmuch as all that which is doon or ſayde in the Churche of Chriſte,<note place="margin">1. Cor. 14.</note> ought to be vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derſtanded and knowen of all the faythfull.<note place="margin">Math. 16. Iohn. 3. Gala. 3. Acts. 2.22 1. Pet. 3. Rom. 8. Gala. 4. Math. 28. Titus. 3.</note> By that Baptiſme wee are chaunged, and tranſformed from the Children of wrath, ſinne, dyuell and perdition, into y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> children of God of grace and ſaluation: For to bee heyres of GOD, and coheyres with Chriſte in eternall lyfe. And there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore it ought to be geuen and beſto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wed onely to reaſonable creatures, which are capable of thoſe thinges, and not vnto vels, or ſuch like things whiche cannot receyue it, nor exer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cyſe the thinges ſygnifyed by the ſame.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="62" type="article">
                  <head>The .lxii. Article.</head>
                  <p>
                     <note place="margin">Mark. 16. Rom. 2. Act. 8.9.10</note>
                     <hi>I</hi> Beléeue that Baptiſme of water not to bee ſo neceſſary vnto ſalua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion
<pb n="30" facs="tcp:13133:42"/> that man cannot be ſaued with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out it, in caſe of neceſſitye:<note place="margin">Mat. 19. 1. Cor. 7.</note> Alſo I doubt not of the ſaluation of the litle Infanntes which dye without Bap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiſme, but that they are ſaued in the fayth of theyr parentes, aſwell as if they were baptiſed, as alſo in tymes paſt the litle Chyldren vnder the lawe whiche dyed without Cir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cumciſion,<note place="margin">2. Reg. 12.</note> were ſaued in the fayth of theyr parentes. I vnderſtande that onely of the children of the faythfull,<note place="margin">Gen. 17. Rom. 4.</note> to whome the promyſes of the Lorde appertayned, and not to the Infidels and reprobate.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="63" type="article">
                  <head>The .lxiii. Article.</head>
                  <p>
                     <hi>I</hi> Beléeue that the holye Sacra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of the Supper,<note place="margin">Math. 26. Mark. 14. Luk. 22. 1. Cor. 12.</note> is a holye and externe Ceremonye, inſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tuted by Ieſus Chriſte in his Goſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pell, one day ebefore his death, vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der the likeneſſe of breade and wine, in remembrance and recordation of his death and paſſion, hauyng and contayning in it the promyſe of the forgeueneſſe of ſynnes, by whych we
<pb facs="tcp:13133:43"/> perticipate truly the body and blood of Ieſus Chriſte,<note place="margin">1. Cor. 10.</note> and are nurriſhed and fed in the Lordes houſe (which is his Church) after that we are entred in the ſame by the Baptiſme. That alſo ought to be geuen and beſtowed vnto all vnder both kindes,<note place="margin">Math. 26. 1. Cor. 11.</note> after the ordi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nance &amp; commaundement of Chriſte, againſt which it is not lawfull to at<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tempt any thing.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="64" type="article">
                  <head>The .lxiiii. Article.</head>
                  <p>
                     <note place="margin">1. Cor. 11. Iereneus. S. Ambro. S. Auguſt. ſ. Chriſoſt. Tertulian.</note>
                     <hi>I</hi> Beléeue that in that holye Sacra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, the ſignes or Symboles are not in any wiſe chainged: but that they abide wholye in theyr nature. That is to ſay, that the bread is not changed nor tranſubſtantiated (as the Caphardes and falſe Doctors haue taught, deceiuing the poore people) into the body of Ieſus Chriſt, neither the wine tranſuſtantiated into hys blood.<note place="margin">Math. 26. Luk. 22. Gen. 17. Exo. 12.19. Oſeas. 4. Rom. 8. 2. Cor. 3.</note> But that the bread abydeth al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wayes bread, and the wine, wine, e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerye one in his proper and firſt na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture. For the wordes which Chriſte ſpake vnto his Apoſtles in geuing
<pb n="31" facs="tcp:13133:43"/> the bread, ſaying: This is my body, I do vnderſtand and beléeue it to be ſpoken by a figure called <hi>Metonimia,</hi> whiche is a kinde of ſpeaking verye common in the holye ſcriptures, as the holy ſcriptures and eccleſiaſticall Doctors, <hi>Ireneus, Cyprian, Tertu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lian, Ambroſe, Auguſtine, Chryſoſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tome</hi> and ſuch other, haue vnderſtan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded and declared by theyr writinges, who lyued before the Counſell of <hi>La<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teran,</hi> in which was concluded y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> tran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſubſtantiation of the bread into the body of Chriſte and the wine into his blood,<note place="margin">De ſum. Trin. tit. 1. Cap. 1.</note> and geuen for an article of faith to the great diſhonor of God, and of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fence of all the Church, in the yeere of our Lorde .1050. by pope Leo the ninth, in whiche tyme Sathan was then let looſe, as was foreſhewed in the Apocalips,<note place="margin">Apo. 20.</note> &amp; troubled the Church of Chriſte more, then it was before.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="65" type="article">
                  <head>The .lxv. Article.</head>
                  <p>
                     <hi>I</hi> Beléeue that all that Sacrament lieth and conſiſteth in vſing,<note place="margin">Act. 2.20. Luk. 22. 1. Cor. 11.</note> ſo that in not vſing, that bread and that
<pb facs="tcp:13133:44"/> wine do differ nothing from other co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                     <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon bread and wine,<note place="margin">S. Auguſt Origine.</note> which men vſe commonly in their houſes, &amp; therfore I beléeue not, that the body of Chriſt is contayned, tyed, or encloſed, in that bread, vnder that bread, or with that bread: neither the blood, in that wine, vnder that wine, or with that wine. But I beleeue and confeſſe his body to be in heauen at the right hande of the Father (as we haue declared be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore) and that as often and when we vſe that bread and that wine,<note place="margin">Article. 37.</note> accor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding to the ordinance and inſtitution of Chriſt, that truly and indéede, we receyue his body and his blood.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="66" type="article">
                  <head>The .lxvi. Article.</head>
                  <p>
                     <note place="margin">Iob. 6. 1. Cor. 10.</note>
                     <hi>I</hi> Beleeue that that receyuing is doone not carnallye or corporally, but in ſpyrite, thorow a lyuelye and true fayth.<note place="margin">S. Auguſt</note> That is to ſaye, that the body and blood of Chriſte, are not geuen to the mouth, or belly, for the nurriſhing of the bodye, but to our fayth, for nurriſhing of the ſpirite, and inwarde manne to eternall lyfe.
<pb n="32" facs="tcp:13133:44"/> And for to doo that, it is not neede<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full that Chriſte deſcende from hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uen for to come vnto vs: but that we aſcende vnto him,<note place="margin">Phil. 3. Coloſ. 3.</note> addreſſing our hartes thorow lyuely fayth an hygh to the right hand of the father, where he ſitteth, from whence we looke for our redemption: and not to ſéeke it in theſe corruptible elementes.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="67" type="article">
                  <head>The .lxvii. Article.</head>
                  <p>
                     <hi>I</hi> Beléeue that that holye Supper,<note place="margin">1. Cor. 11. Rom. 8.</note> is a Sacrament of fayth vnto the faythfull onely, and not for the in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fidelles: in which one fyndeth and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceyueth,<note place="margin">S. Auguſt</note> that that one bringeth thy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, and no more, except it be per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>aduenture augmentation of fayth, grace and vertue, and therfore in the ſame,<note place="margin">Iohn. 6. 1. Cor. 10.</note> thoſe onelye doo receyue and finde Ieſus Chriſt to ſaluatio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> which bringe it with them thorow a lyuely and true fayth.<note place="margin">Iohn. 13. 1. Cor. 11.</note> But others doo finde and receyue there onely the externe and viſible Symboles, and that to their condempnation, as <hi>Iudas</hi> and o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther ſuch wicked and reprobate.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="68" type="article">
                  <pb facs="tcp:13133:45"/>
                  <head>The .lxviii. Article.</head>
                  <p>
                     <note place="margin">Luk. 22. 1. Cor. 11. Iereneus.</note>
                     <hi>I</hi> Beléeue that that Sacrament con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taineth two thinges, one which is terreſtriall, carnall and vſible, ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther which is celeſtiall, ſpirituall and inuiſible: and I do confeſſe that as our body and inward man receyueth the terreſtriall and viſible thing which is the bread and the wine, by which it is alymented and nurriſhed, that alſo verely our ſpirit and inward man re<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ceiued the celeſtiall &amp; ſpirituall thing, ſignified by the bread &amp; wine,<note place="margin">Ephe. 5.</note> to wete, the body and blood of Chriſte: So that we are made one with him, bone of his bones, fleſh of his fleſh, perticipa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting with him in all righteouſneſſe and other vertues, gifts and goodnes, which the eternall father hath put in him.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="69" type="article">
                  <head>The .lxix. Article.</head>
                  <p>
                     <note place="margin">1. Cor. 10. Exo. 1.2.6.17.</note>
                     <hi>I</hi> Beléeue that the holy Fathers, Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>triarkes, Prophetes and all other faythfull and good people, which haue
<pb n="33" facs="tcp:13133:45"/> gone before vs and are dead in faith, dyd knowe farre of him that ſhoulde come, to wete, Chriſte,<note place="margin">Hebr. 11. Ioh. 6.14. Ephe. 3. Rom. 1.3. Gala. 3. Ephe. 4. 1. Cor. 10. Num. 20.</note> by the worde and fayth: and did receyue aſmuch, and the verie ſame, which wee re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceyue nowe by the Sacramentes: who alſo were of the verye ſame Churche, fayth and lawe, of which we are: Chriſtians as wee are, and haue vſed the ſame Sacramentes in figure, which we vſe in déede.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="70" type="article">
                  <head>The .lxx. Article.</head>
                  <p>
                     <hi>I</hi> Beléeue that vnto that holy Table ought to be admytted,<note place="margin">1. Cor. 5.10.11. 2. Theſ. 3.</note> but onelie the faythfull, the true contryte and penitent, and all that are vnworthy to be reiected, for feare leaſt they de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fyle &amp; contamynate the holy meates, which the Lorde geueth not,<note place="margin">Math. 7.15</note> but vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to this domeſticall and faithfull. I call vnworthy, all Infydels, Idola<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters, blaſphemers, contempners of God, Heretikes, and all people which make ſectes, for to breake the vnitie of the Churche: all periured perſones, all thoſe which are rebel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lious
<pb facs="tcp:13133:46"/> againſt their fathers and mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers, and their ſuperiors, all ſediti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous perſons, quarrellers, fighters, whoremongers, théeues, rauiſhers, couetous, droonkerdes, gluttons, and generallye, all thoſe which leade a ſlaunderous and dyſſolute lyfe. Such manner of people haue no parte nor portion in the kingdom of God,<note place="margin">Gala. 5. Ephe. 5.</note> ther<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore they ought to be reiected and put out of the Church:<note place="margin">Rom. 16. 1. Cor. 5.6. 2. Cor. 2.6 2. Theſ. 3.</note> with whome it is not lawfull to frequent, eate, drinke, or contract allyaunce, except it bee peraduenture to win and leade them to repentaunce.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="71" type="article">
                  <head>The .lxxi. Article.</head>
                  <p>
                     <hi>I</hi> Beléeue that the popiſhe Maſſe<note place="margin">The Maſſe</note> is not, nor can not be the holy Sup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>per of the Lorde. But a méere inuention of lying and wicked men: altogether contrarie vnto the ſame, as the nyght to the daye, <hi>Beliall</hi> to Chriſte: The which ſhall be knowen of all men, more clearelie then the noone day, by the conference and col<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lation made betwéene the inſtitution
<pb n="34" facs="tcp:13133:46"/> of that Supper, recyted and written by the Euangeliſtes,<note place="margin">Math. 26. Mark. 14. Luk. 22. 1. Cor. 11.</note> and chieflye by the Apoſtle Saint <hi>Paul,</hi> and the cele<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bration of the Maſſe. Therefore it is not a remembraunce of the true ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crifice, that is to ſaye, of the death and Paſſion of Chriſte, as the holye Supper is.<note place="margin">Pſal. 115. Rom. 3.5. Colo. 1. Hebr. 9.10.12.13. 1. Pete. 1. 1. Iohn. 2. Apoſ. 1.15.</note> But a renouncing of the ſame, for ſo much as it attrybuteth that which belongeth vnto the onelie blood of Chriſt ſhedde vpon the croſſe, to wete, ſatiſfaction, purgation, and remiſſion of ſinnes, with collation of grace: and maketh vs to worſhip the creature, in ſteede of the Creator, a péece of breade in ſtéede of Ieſus Chriſte our onely Lord, ſauiour, and redéemer.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="72" type="article">
                  <head>The .lxxii. Article.</head>
                  <p>
                     <hi>I</hi> Beléeue the thirde marke of the Church (which is the Eccleſiaſtical diſcipline) to be greatly profitable,<note place="margin">Math. 28. Luke. 17. Iohn. 20. 1. Cor. 5.10.14.</note> yea, neceſſary in y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> Catholike church, for y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> conſolatio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> of the good, &amp; correctio of the wicked:<note place="margin">Acts. 5.8. 1. Cor. 5.</note> The which alſo I re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceyue, &amp; ſubmyt my ſelfe to the ſame,
<pb facs="tcp:13133:47"/> knowing that it is the ordinaunce of Chriſte in the Goſpell:<note place="margin">1. Cor. 2. 1. Timo. 1. 1. Cor. 14.</note> The which alſo was practiſed by the Apoſtles in the primatiue Church, that all might be done honeſtlie and in good order: which is an honeſt and neceſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſarie thing in euery Congregation.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="73" type="article">
                  <head>The .lxxiii. Article.</head>
                  <p>
                     <note place="margin">Math. 16.</note>
                     <hi>I</hi> Beléeue the power to bynde and looſe, excommunicate, and abſolue, which we call commonly the keies of the Churche,<note place="margin">Math. 18. Iohn 20.</note> to bee geuen of God, not vnto one man or two, or to any particularly, but vnto al the Church, that is to ſaye, to all the faythfull and beléeuing in Chriſte, not for to deſtroye,<note place="margin">1. Cor. 10. 2. Cor. 6.</note> waſte or conſume, but for to buylde vp and aduaunce it altoge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther. Therefore I ſaye and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſe that the excommunication or ab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolution of the ſame, ought not, nor can not be geuen at the appetyte, or wyll of ſome perticularlie, but by the conſent of all the Churche, or at leaſt of the greateſt, beſt, and holyeſt parte
<pb n="35" facs="tcp:13133:47"/> of the ſame, congregated, and aſſem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bled in the name of Chriſt with pray<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ers.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="74" type="article">
                  <head>The .lxxiiii. Article.</head>
                  <p>
                     <hi>I</hi> Beléeue that exco<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>munication exe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cuted duelye,<note place="margin">Math. 18. Iohn. 20. Math. 16. Acts. 5.8. 1. Cor. 5.</note> according as Ieſus Chriſte hath declared, and com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maunded in his Goſpell, to bee of ſo great aucthoritie, power &amp; ſtrength, that it can ſhutte men out of heauen. So that all thoſe which are by law<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full excommunication reiected, and put out of the Church mylitant, they ſhall be alſo reiected and put from the Church tryumphant,<note place="margin">2<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> Cor. 2. Math. 18. 1. Tim. 1.</note> which is in heauen (except they repent) that is a ſharpe ſworde for to c<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>tte away the rotten members of the myſticall bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy of Chriſte, which is his Churche.<note place="margin">Math. 16. Acts. 5.8. 1. Cor. 5. 2. Theſ. 3.</note> A key for to ſhutte vp the heauens a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt the wicked, and a rodde to chaſtice &amp; correct them: The which yet neuertheleſſe, is not made for to confounde them, but as a ſpyrituall medicine for to amend, relieue, heale,
<pb facs="tcp:13133:48"/> and to ſet them vp againe, fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> which they are fallen.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="75" type="article">
                  <head>The .lxxv. Article.</head>
                  <p>
                     <note place="margin">Math. 18.</note>
                     <hi>I</hi> Beléeue that that excommunica<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on (which is the laſt ſtaffe of the Churche) ought not, nor can not be caſt againſt any perſon,<note place="margin">1. Cor. 5.</note> which firſt hath not receyued and made pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſion of the faith and chriſtian Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligion. As alſo it cannot be pronoun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ced for euerie ſmall thing,<note place="margin">2. Theſſ. 3.</note> as are, debtes, or other lyke thinges. Nor alſo be executed againſt all ſinners,<note place="margin">Acts. 5.8. 1. Tim. 1. 2. Iohn. 1. Math. 18. Luke. 17.</note> but onely againſt publycke, rebelli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous, and obſtynate ſinners, towards whome the worde of God, and the brotherly correction, commau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ded by Chriſt in the Goſpel, taketh no place. Wherfore all thoſe do greatly abuſe that ſtaffe which do excommunicate the Chriſtians,<note place="margin">Iohn. 9.12.16.</note> for ſmal things, with out hauing ſuffred the brotherly cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rection. In lyke manner alſo, thoſe which do excommunicate the Iewes, Turkes, Heathens, &amp; other Infidels: yea, alſo the Flyes, and other brute
<pb n="36" facs="tcp:13133:48"/> beaſtes, wylling to caſt &amp; put out of the chriſtian Church, all that which neuer was in it.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="76" type="article">
                  <head>The .lxxvi. Article.</head>
                  <p>
                     <hi>I</hi> Beléeue beſides the ſame,<note place="margin">Ephe. 4. Ioh. 13.15. Roma. 12.13.15. Gala. 6. Ioh. 2.3.4.</note> that the vnitie of ſpyrite &amp; wyll, peace con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>corde and loue, that is to ſaye, true loue and brotherly delection, amiable &amp; the mutuall ſupporting the one to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wardes the other, is alſo one of the markes and ſignes of the true calho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lyke Church, &amp; of the faithfull childre<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> of God, by which they are known to be of the ſchoole, &amp; number of the Diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciples of Ieſus Chriſt:<note place="margin">Iere. 7. Math. 7.21 25. Luke. 6.13. Rom. 2. 1. Cor. 13.</note> And we muſt not glory of the tytle of Chriſtian, or of the fayth, ſaying: I beléeue, I be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>léeue: except we haue that loue, peace, charitie, and true vnitie of the harte together, agréeing the one with the other in all good works:<note place="margin">Iames. 2. Iohn. 8.14. 1. Ioh. 2.3.4.</note> For the true faith neuer goeth w<hi rend="sup">t</hi>out theſe things, by which alſo, it declareth &amp; manife<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſteth it ſelf vnto al. Theſe are y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſigns &amp; marks of the true chriſtian church, to which ſhe is bound &amp; tyed, and not
<pb facs="tcp:13133:49"/> to a certaine place,<note place="margin">S. Auguſt.</note> tyme or perſons. And there ſhe is perfect, where theſe markes are founde and exerciſed: and not otherwiſe, that if one of that fayle, then it is not perfect. And al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>though that, that total perfection can be founde for the eſtate of this pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent world, in the Church myllytant, yet the faulte ought to be acknowled<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ged before the Lorde, and to endeuor to remedy and ſet it in good order.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="77" type="article">
                  <head>The .lxxvii. Article.</head>
                  <p>
                     <note place="margin">Luke. 22. Math. 28. Mark. 16. Luke. 24. Math. 10. Mark. 6. Luke. 9.10. Ephe. 6.</note>
                     <hi>I</hi> Beléeue &amp; receyue in that Church two ſwordes, that is to ſaye, two powers, the one Eccleſiaſtical and Spyrituall, the which conſiſteth in the onely adminiſtration of the word and Sacramentes, ſhe caryeth, ney<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther rodde, nor ſtaffe, other then the tongue, &amp; ſhe vſeth none other knyfe then the ſworde of the ſpyrite,<note place="margin">Leuit. 21. Iere. 23. Ezec. 34. 3. Reg. 2. 1. Tim. 3. Titus. 1.</note> which is the worde of God. In lyke manner I confeſſe that all thoſe which haue that ſworde betwéene their handes, ought to be irreprehenſible, aſwel in
<pb n="37" facs="tcp:13133:49"/> their lyfe as doctrine: Otherwiſe, one ought to depoſe &amp; put them from their offices, and to put and ſubſty<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tute other better, in their places. The other power is pollitike,<note place="margin">Rom. 11.</note> to wete, the Magiſtrate, as touching externe and ciuill things, for to geue according to Iuſtice vnto euerie one that appertaineth vnto him.<note place="margin">1. Pet. 2.</note>
                  </p>
               </div>
               <div n="78" type="article">
                  <head>The .lxxviii. Article.</head>
                  <p>
                     <hi>I</hi> Beléeue that the Magiſtrate,<note place="margin">Exo. 18.2<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>. Deu. 16.17. Prou. 8. Eſai. 1. Dam. 2. Roma. 13. 1. Peter. 2. Mat. 17.22.</note> is one ordained of God in his church for to defende the good people, and to chaſtice and puniſhe the wicked: To whome alſo we muſt render and geue the tribute, honour and reue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rence, and obey him in all thinges, which are not againſt the worde of God.<note place="margin">Mark. 12. Luke. 26. Iohn. 18. Ephe. 6. Coloſ. 3. 1. Peter. 2.</note> And I do vnderſtande that not onelye of the faythfull Magiſtrate: But alſo of the vnfaithfull, wicked and Tyrant: to whome alſo we muſt obey as to the Lorde, in all thinges: ſo that hee commaunde nothing a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt the worde of the Lorde: For then wee ought rather to obey God
<pb facs="tcp:13133:50"/> then men, after the example of the A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſtles <hi>Peter</hi> and <hi>Iohn.</hi>
                  </p>
               </div>
               <div n="79" type="article">
                  <head>The <hi>.lxxix.</hi> Article.</head>
                  <p>
                     <note place="margin">Rom. 13. Deut. 7.12.17. 3. Reg. 15. 4. Reg. 18.23. Nehemias. Eſai. 49. 4. Reg 23. Nehem. 8.</note>
                     <hi>I</hi> Beléeue that vnto the Magiſtrate belongeth not onely to haue regard ouer pollityke thinges, but alſo o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer the Eccleſiaſticall thinges, for to take away and put downe all Idola<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trie, and all falſe ſeruing of God. For to deſtroy the kingdom of Antichriſt, and all falſe doctrine: and to promote the glorie of God, and to aduance the kingdome of Chriſte: to cauſe the worde of the Goſpell to be preached euery where, and to maintayne the ſame eue<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> vnto death:<note place="margin">Deut. 13.</note> Alſo to chaſtice and puniſh the falſe Prophets, which leade the poore people after Idolles and ſtraunge Gods: and which in ſtéede of the Goſpell, do preache and teach the fables &amp; traditions of men, to the diſhonor of God, and of Ieſus Chriſte his ſonne, to the great euyll and offence of the hearers, and to the ruyne of all the Church.<note place="margin">Roma. 13. 1. Pete. 2.</note> Vnto that Magiſtrate, euerie perſon of what
<pb n="38" facs="tcp:13133:50"/> eſtate or conditio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ſo euer he be,<note place="margin">Exod. 22. Prou. 16.19.20. Baruc. 2. 2. Cro. 20. Pſal. 82. Eſai. 45. Roma. 14. Ierem. 29. 1. Tim. 2.</note> ought to be ſubiect &amp; obeye him in all honeſt and reaſonable things, for that he re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>teth the perſon of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> great Lord, before whome euerye knée ought to bowe: Therefore he ought not to be forgotten in our prayers, for that the Lord wil dyrect him in al his wayes, and that we maye ioyne together in good peace and tra<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>quilitie vnder him.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="80" type="article">
                  <head>The .lxxx. Article.</head>
                  <p>
                     <hi>I</hi> Beléeue that that Magiſtrate (as alſo the ſacraments and other lyke things) was ordayned of the Lord for to ayde the imperfection of man in the corrupt nature after the ſinne,<note place="margin">Deut. 17. 1. Reg. 8.</note> whome the faythfull (after he hath proued all other meanes) may holyly and iuſtlye vſe in all controuerſies,<note place="margin">1. Cor. 6. Rom. 13.</note> which maye happen betwéene him and his neighbor, and for to make an ende and peace in all things. Wher<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore hee which in neceſſitie wyll not vſe him, ought rather to bee iudged an Annabaptiſt, then a Chriſtian.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="81" type="article">
                  <pb facs="tcp:13133:51"/>
                  <head>The .lxxxi. Article.</head>
                  <p>
                     <note place="margin">Exod. 22. 4. Reg. 23. 2. Cron. 15. 1. Eſdr. 10. Hebr. 6. Deut. 6.10. Leuit. 19. Exo. 20.23. Math. 5.</note>
                     <hi>I</hi> Beléeue that the Magiſtrate, ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lylie maye geue the oathe vnto the faithful in iudgement, for to know the trueth, and to make an ende of all controuerſies and dyfferences be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>twéene men, the which ought to bée done by the onely name of the lyuing God: for aſmuch as it is the thyrde commaundement of the fyrſt Table. And although that the Chriſtian per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fection be,<note place="margin">Iam. 5.</note> to ſaye ſimply, yea, yea: nay, nay: without ſwearing any thing at all.<note place="margin">Iere. 4.12. Eſay. 9. Gene. 22.</note> Yet neuertheleſſe, the faithfull maye holylie vſe an oath in place and tyme, with diſcretion, in the feare of God, for honeſt, iuſt and true thinges,<note place="margin">Hebr. 6. Rom. 1.9. 2. Cor. 1. Gala. 1. Eccle. 23.27</note> for to confyrme the trueth, when the honour of God, or the health of our neyghbour depen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deth on it, and not otherwyſe. For the man that accuſtometh him ſelfe to ſwearing ſhall be filled with ini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quitie, and the plague ſhall neuer de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>part from his houſe.<note place="margin">Deut. 23. Ioſua. 4. Pſalm. 76. Eccle. 5. Malac. 1. Math. 5.23</note> I do alſo con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſe, that as all oathes, vowes and
<pb n="39" facs="tcp:13133:51"/> promyſes (made accordinge to the Lordes worde) be it vnto God, or to men, are obligatorie, and ought to be kepte and obſerued inuyolablie. Alſo that thoſe which are made without,<note place="margin">Iudges. 11. Math. 14. Acts. 23.</note> or againſt the worde and commaun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dement of God (as are the monaſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>call vowes and other ſuch like, which promiſe impoſſible thinges and alto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gether againſt the word of the Lord) do bynde nothing at all: but maye be holylie broken and vyolated:<note place="margin">1. Reg. 25.</note> For in wicked promiſes, and in fooliſhe and indiſcrete vowes, the faithfull, pru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dent and wyſe man maye change his mynde.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="82" type="article">
                  <head>The .lxxxii. Article.</head>
                  <p>
                     <hi>I</hi> Beléeue &amp; confeſſe that the eſtate of mariage is honorable amongſt all men, and the bed vndefiled,<note place="margin">Hebr. 13. Gene. 2. Math. 19. 1. Cor. 7. 1. Tim. 3. Titus. 1.</note> ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly and cleane, ordayned and inſtitu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted of God for generation, and for to auoyde fornication, from which none ought nor can not be reiected (except there be ſome iuſt and lawfull let by the worde of God,<note place="margin">Leuit. 18. Gen. 1.8.9. 1. Cor. 7. Sapi. 8. Math. 19.</note>) but ought to be
<pb facs="tcp:13133:52"/> free for al men of what eſtate or con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dition ſoeuer he be. For it is a great deale better to marie then to burne. And therefore thoſe which haue not the gyft of contynencie,<note place="margin">1. Cor. 7. Sapi. 8. Mat. 19. 1. Cor. 7.</note> are bound to marie: leaſt the temple of the holye Ghoſt, that is to ſaye our bodyes, be polluted or prophaned.<note place="margin">1. Cor. 3.6.</note>
                  </p>
               </div>
               <div n="83" type="article">
                  <head>The .lxxxiii. Article.</head>
                  <p>
                     <note place="margin">1. Tim. 4. 1. Tim. 3. Rom. 14.</note>
                     <hi>I</hi> Do alſo beléeue that the forbidding of mariage to certaine perſons, as alſo the forbidding of meates, the dif<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ference of daies, apparel, and all ſuch lyke thinges,<note place="margin">Malac. 1.2. Baruc. 2. Eſai. 1.9. Iere. 6.13. Oſeas. 6. Amos. 5. Gala. 4. Colloſ. 2. Roma. 14. 1. Cor. 8. 1. Tim. 4.</note> is the diuellyſh doctrine of Antechriſte, altogether contrary to the chriſtian and euangelicall lyber<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie, geuen by Ieſus Chriſt, the which deliuereth vs from all thoſe legalles, &amp; externall ceremonies, and putteth vs at lybertie to vſe all things (with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out offe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce neuertheleſſe of our neigh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bour) with geuing of thankes vnto God. For all thinges are made holy by the word and praier, to him which
<pb n="40" facs="tcp:13133:52"/> hath known and receiued the trueth. Wherfore to compel and conſtraine the chriſtians to ſuch things, that is, to take from them, &amp; rob them of the chriſtian liberty, to tyrannyſe them,<note place="margin">Apo. 13.17. Gala. 3.</note> and bring the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> vnder againe the curſe of the lawe, of which Chriſte by his death and paſſio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> hath deliuered them. And it is a true marke and note of antechriſt.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="84" type="article">
                  <head>The .lxxxiiii. Article.</head>
                  <p>
                     <hi>I</hi> Beléeue y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> the pure and true ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uing of God conſiſteth not in thoſe ceremonies &amp; outward things,<note place="margin">Eſai. 1. Iere. 6. Math. 6.23 Luke. 17. 3. Reg. 18.</note> nor in much babling, and mumbling of long prayers, nor in crying and how<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling in the Temple, lyke vnto Aſſes, or the Prieſtes of <hi>Baall.</hi>
                     <note place="margin">Iohn. 5.6. Rom. 14. Acte. 7.17. Gala. 5.</note> But in ſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rituall thinges, as are the liuely and true faith in God, and in his word by his Sonne Ieſus Chriſte, working by charity towardes their neyghbor, in true and perfect inuocation of his name,<note place="margin">Gene. 4.12.21. Pſalm. 50. Ioel. 2.</note> with obedyence to his com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maundementes, and humility of ſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rite according to his worde. For as
<pb facs="tcp:13133:53"/> God is a ſpyrite,<note place="margin">Iohn. 4. 2. Cor. 3.</note> ſo woulde he be ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ued in ſpyrite and trueth.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="85" type="article">
                  <head>The .lxxxv. Article.</head>
                  <p>
                     <note place="margin">Eſai. 1. Ierem. 6. Amos. 5. Eſai. 37. Iere. 2.7.9.32. Eze. 5.6.16.</note>
                     <hi>I</hi> Beléeue that all the ſeruyng of GOD which is done without hys worde and commaundement to be Idolatrie and wickedneſſe. I call I<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dolatry (after the faſhion of the Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phetes) not onely that which is done to the honor of an Idoll, or of ſtrange Gods. But alſo that which is done for the honor of the liuing God, with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out his worde and commaundement. Therefore Idolaters are not onelie thoſe which do worſhyp and ſerue I<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dols and ſtraunge Gods,<note place="margin">3. Reg. 3.12 15.22. 4. Reg. 12.14.18.23. Eſai. 29. Math. 15.</note> as the Eth<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nickes, Panymes and ſuch lyke: But alſo all thoſe, which worſhyppe and ſerue the true God of heauen, after their fantaſie, or traditions of men, without fayth, without the worde, and otherwiſe then God commau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ded. And on the other ſyde, I call thoſe faithfull which do acknowledge and ſerue one onely God of heauen, after his worde and commaundement,<note place="margin">1. Cor. 10. Gala. 2.</note> of
<pb n="41" facs="tcp:13133:53"/> whome all the works aſwell externall and internall, corporall as ſpyrituall,<note place="margin">Colloſ. 3. Rom. 12. 1. Cor. 7. Ephe. 4.</note> are the true ſeruing of the Lorde, for that they are done in the fayth of the ſonne of God, and according to the vo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cation of the Lord, according to which euery faithfull perſon ought to walk.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="86" type="article">
                  <head>The .lxxxvi. Article.</head>
                  <p>
                     <hi>I</hi> Beléeue and confeſſe,<note place="margin">Deut. 13. Eſai. 52. 1. Cor. 10. 2. Cor. 6.</note> that it is not lawfull for any Chriſtian, to be aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiſtant, neither in ſpirite nor body, to the ſacrifices of Idolaters, nor alſo to enter into their Temples, whyleſt they are doing their Idolatries &amp; Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crifices: except it be for to rebuke the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>,<note place="margin">3. Reg. 13. 4. Reg. 10. Actes. 3.9.17.19. Gene. 2. Iob. 10. 1. Cor. 3.6. Ephe. 5. 1. Cor. 15. Iohn. 5.11. 1. Theſ. 4.</note> in ſhewing them their abuſe, and to teach them y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> trueth, as the holy Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phets and Apoſtles haue done, and not for to dyſſemble as Hypocrites. For if the body be a creature of God (as it is) as the ſoule is the Temple of the holy Ghoſt, and member of the miſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>call body of Chriſte: If it muſt one day ryſe againe, and poſſeſſe the eternall lyfe with the ſoule, it muſt alſo neceſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſarily be, that it be altogether geuen
<pb facs="tcp:13133:54"/> vnto the ſeruing of God in this world with the ſoule and ſpyrite: Otherwiſe they cannot be ioygned together after the generall reſurrection: but being ſeperated, the one ſhould be in heauen with God whome be loued, and the o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther in hell with the diuell whome hee ſerued:<note place="margin">Math. 10. Rom. 10. Luke. 12.</note> the which is an impoſſyble thing. Therefore I ſaye, that all thoſe diſſymulations to bee a verie renoun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cing of Chriſte and of his Goſpel.<note place="margin">Gala. 2. 2. Math. 6.</note> In lyke manner I beleeue &amp; confeſſe that all thoſe fayninges and falſe ſhewes, by which the veritie of the Goſpell is hidden, and the word of God deſpiſed, or by which the ignoraunt and Infidel is confirmed in his error, or by which the weake is offended, are not of God, but of Satan, altogether contrary vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to the truth of the word.<note place="margin">1. Reg. 18.</note> Therfore we muſt not halt on both ſides, but go vp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rightly before that great God, which ſéeth,<note place="margin">Dan. 13. Heb. 4.</note> beholdeth, &amp; knoweth all things: yea, before they are begun.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="87" type="article">
                  <head>The .lxxxvii. Article.</head>
                  <p>
                     <note place="margin">Sap. 14. Pſalm. 97.</note>
                     <hi>I</hi> Do alſo beléeue that the beginning of all Idolatryes, was the excogita<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion
<pb n="42" facs="tcp:13133:54"/> and fyrſt inuention of Images,<note place="margin">Eſai. 40. Oſc. 10. Baruc. 6.</note> the which alſo were made to the abho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mination and offence of the Soules of men, and are as ſnares and nettes to the féete of the ignoraunt, for to make them ſtumble. Therefore they ought not to be honoured, ſerued, adored,<note place="margin">Pſalm. 114.</note> nor ſuffred in the Temples or Churches,<note place="margin">Deut. 7.16.27, 29.</note> nor in the places where the Chriſtia<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s doo aſſemble them ſelues together for to heare and vnderſtand the word, but altogether to be taken away &amp; deſtroi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed,<note place="margin">Exo. 20.23. Deut. 7. 4. Reg. 18.23.</note> as the ſeconde commaundement of God doth well declare, and that by the publyke authoritie of the Magiſtrate, and not by the priuate authoritie of one perticular man.<note place="margin">Deut. 17. Sapi. 14. Pſal. 114. 1. Iohn. 5.</note> For the woodde of the gybbit by which one doth Iuſtice, is bleſſed of God: But the Image made with mans hande, is curſſed of God, and he that maketh it with it. Therefore we ought to kéepe our ſel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ues from Images aboue all thinges.</p>
               </div>
            </div>
            <div type="introduction">
               <p>BEholde what I beleeue of the catholike Church, and of the thinges concerning the ſame: and that is for the fourth point
<pb facs="tcp:13133:55"/> of my faith. Nowe remaineth to ſpeake of the fruites proceeding from it, and what I receyue by that faith, which are three in number. VVherof the firſt is.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="commentary">
               <head>The forgeueneſſe of ſinnes.</head>
               <div n="88" type="article">
                  <head>The .lxxxviii. Article.</head>
                  <p>
                     <note place="margin">Iob 15.25. Pſal. 14.15. Roma. 3. 1. Iohn. 1. Eſai. 53. 1. Peter. 2. Gene 8.9. Pro. 20. Ephe. 2. Iohn. 8. Rom. 3.</note>
                     <hi>I</hi> Beléeue y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> all thoſe which are come, and which ſhall come of the race or lyne of <hi>Adam,</hi> generallye are con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceiued and borne in iniquity &amp; corrup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion (except one onely Ieſus Chriſte) and that they are all ſinners &amp; tranſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>greſſors of the lawe and wyll of God: And according to their nature, corrup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted, the chyldren of wrath, worthy of Gods iudgeme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t, of condempnation &amp; eternall death,<note place="margin">Iohn. 3.</note> hauing all néede of the grace &amp; mercy of God, and of the blood of Chriſte to be ſhead. For God hath encloſed all men vnder ſinne,<note place="margin">Rom. 11. Gala. 3.</note> that hée ſhoulde ſhewe mercie vnto all thorow Ieſus Chriſt our Lorde.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="89" type="article">
                  <pb n="43" facs="tcp:13133:55"/>
                  <head>The <hi>.lxxxix.</hi> Article.</head>
                  <p>
                     <hi>I</hi> Beléeue that the knowledge of ſin,<note place="margin">Rom. 3.7. Ierem. 31. Mich. 7. Ioh. 3.5.10. Act. 4.5.10 Ro. 4.5.10. Ephe. 2. Titus. 3.</note> procéedeth from the law, but the for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>geuenes &amp; pardon of the ſame com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>meth from the Goſpell, and is geuen vnto vs thorow the only grace &amp; mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cie of God, in the blood of Ieſus Chriſt, kéeping the faith that we haue in him, by which wee are reputed righteous before God: and not thorowe our good works or merites, nor by the merites of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> pureſt creature celeſtiall or terre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtiall: For I do not know,<note place="margin">Eſai. 53. Rom. 5.6. Ephe. 5. Hebr. 9.10.</note> nor receyue any other merites the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> thoſe of my good Lord, maſter and onely ſauiour Ieſus Chriſte, who hath merited &amp; ſatiſfied aboundantly for vs, and hath payd the debt, for all his,<note place="margin">1. Peter. 2. 1. Iohn. 2. Coloſ. 2.</note> in cancelating y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> hand wryting and obligation which was a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt vs, and taking it away fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the midſt of vs, hath fixed it in the Croſſe.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="90" type="article">
                  <head>The <hi>.lxxxx.</hi> Article.</head>
                  <p>
                     <hi>I</hi> Beléeue that that iuſtifying fayth,<note place="margin">Math. 16. Iohn. 6.</note> is a pure &amp; ſinguler gyft of God, the
<pb facs="tcp:13133:56"/> which is commonly geuen by the hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring of the word,<note place="margin">Ephe. 2. Roma. 10. Hebr. 12.</note> vpon which onely it is builded, and not vpon the doctrines and traditions of men.<note place="margin">Fayth. Roma 8. Gala. 4. Iohn. 3. Math. 7. Roma. 5. Ezech. 18. 1. Timo. 1. Iohn. 1.3. Gala. 3.</note> I call the iuſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fying faith, a certayne aſſuraunce and ſure peſwaſion of the good wyll, loue, grace, goodnes and mercy of God to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wardes vs, by which we are aſſured and verely perſwaded in our harts, of the mercy, fauour and beneuolence of God the Father, that he is for vs, to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards vs, &amp; againſt vs, and wil be vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to vs a mercifull father,<note place="margin">Ephe. 2. 2. Timo. 1. Titus. 3.</note> to pardon our ſinnes, &amp; to geue grace to adopt vs for his children, and to conſtitute vs to be his heyres in the eternall life, and that altogether fréely,<note place="margin">Mat. 17.21. Luke. 17. Mark. 9. Philip. 4.</note> in his ſonne, and tho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>row his onely ſonne Ieſus Chriſt our Lorde, and not thorow our merites or good workes. That faith can doo all thinges,<note place="margin">Luke. 17. Marke. 9. Philip. 4.</note> and nothing is impoſſible to it: the which is neuer perfect nor great inough in vs, therefore we ought al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wayes to pray with the Apoſtles, ſay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing: Lord encreaſe our faith, helpe our vnbeléefe.<note place="margin">Luke. 17. Iohn. 1.36.20. Acts. 10.15.</note> For that onely doth comfort vs, maketh vs holy, righteous, and a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>greeable before the Lorde, doth make
<pb n="44" facs="tcp:13133:56"/> and declare vs to bee the chyldren of God, and heyres of eternall life.<note place="margin">Rom. 1.14. Gala. 3.4. Hebr. 11.</note> The which alſo is the mother, the begyn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning and roote of all good workes,<note place="margin">Roma. 14</note> as infydelitie is the fountayne and roote of all euylles.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="91" type="article">
                  <head>The <hi>.lxxxxi.</hi> Article.</head>
                  <p>
                     <hi>I</hi> Beléeue moreouer,<note place="margin">Math. 7.19 21.25. Ioh. 3.8.10 13.14. Roma. 2.12 1. Cor. 13. Gala. 5.6. Woorkes.</note> that the good workes are not ſuperfluous, vaine nor vnprofitable, but neceſſarie to ſaluation: I call good works, not thoſe which are done after the fantaſie or commaundement of men, but thoſe only which God hath co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>maunded to be be done, by his worde,<note place="margin">Roma. 14. Luke. 17. Eſai. 64. Gala. 5.</note> the which ought to be done, not for to merite any thing towardes the Lorde, or for to auoyde eternall condempnation: But onelye, becauſe that God hath commaunded them:<note place="margin">Exo. 20. 1. Theſ. 4. Ioh. 14.15. Math. 5. Ezech. 16. Roma. 2.</note> And for to teſtifie the loue which we haue vnto the Lord, and the obedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence vnto his worde and commaunde<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment: And to the ende that in vs and by vs hee be glorifyed, and our neigh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bours, aſwell faithfull as vnfaithfull,
<pb facs="tcp:13133:57"/> maye be edifyed.<note place="margin">1. Pete. 2. Iam. 2.</note> Lykewiſe to ſhewe and manifeſt the faith which we haue in God and in his worde, as the good tree declareth him ſelfe,<note place="margin">Math. 7.</note> and is known by his fruite, and for to render certain and ſure our vocation,<note place="margin">2. Pete. 1.</note> election, and Predeſtination. Theſe are the endes of good workes commaunded of God, and who ſo euer dooth them to any o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther ende,<note place="margin">Gala. 2.5.</note> hee abuſeth, ſinneth, dooth wrong and diſhonor vnto the blood of Chriſte, and diſhonoreth God and his worde. For by his doings he declareth Chriſte to haue dyed in vaine.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="92" type="article">
                  <head>The .lxxxxii. Article.</head>
                  <p>
                     <note place="margin">Eſai. 43. Math. 9. Mark. 2. Luke. 5.7. Mat. 10.16.18. Mark. 16. Luk. 24. Iohn. 20. 1. Iohn. 1.2</note>
                     <hi>I</hi> Beléeue y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> there is no man in this worlde, nor in the other, neyther in heauen nor in the earth, which can forgeue and pardo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> my ſinnes, but one onely God, who alſo hath geuen the power and authoritie vnto the Myni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſters of his worde, to declare vnto the faythfull that beleeue, and which are contrite and penitent, the remiſſion of their ſinnes to be done by grace freely,<note place="margin">Acts. 2.3.5.10.15.</note> in the blood of Chriſte ſhead for them.
<pb n="45" facs="tcp:13133:57"/> And to declare them to bee abſolued from their ſinnes,<note place="margin">2. Cor. 3.5.10.</note> and that altogether by the Miniſter of the worde, in the catholyke Church,<note place="margin">1. Peter. 3.</note> in which that for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>geuenes is made and done, and not o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>therwyſe.<note place="margin">Repenta<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce.</note> But of our parte, is requy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red entyre and true repentaunce. The which hath two partes.<note place="margin">Ezech. 18. Eſai. 55. Acts. 3. Iere. 18. Gene 4. Math. 27.</note> The firſt is contrition, that is to ſaye, know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge, with diſpleaſure and deteſtati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on to ſinne, the which is adminiſtred by the lawe, and cauſeth in vs a deſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>payre, if it be not ayded of the other parte,<note place="margin">Math. 3. Iohn. 3.8. Roma. 5. Iere. 3.</note> which is the lyuelie faith in the mercie of the father, by the blood of Ie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſus Chriſt, the which proceedeth from the Goſpell, that doth comfort vs, and maketh vs to perſyſt and finde grace and fauour before the iudgement of God.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="93" type="article">
                  <head>The .lxxxxiii. Article.</head>
                  <p>
                     <hi>I</hi> Beléeue that the ſinne abydeth al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wayes in man, yea,<note place="margin">Iob. 3.6.7.9. Ierem. 20. Math. 6. Rom. 7.8. 1. Iohn. 3.</note> vnto thoſe that are ſanctified, after the regenerati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on made by the baptiſme and the holie ſpyrite, the which neuertheleſſe is not
<pb facs="tcp:13133:58"/> imputed vnto them,<note place="margin">Math. 21. 1. Iohn. 3.</note> thorow the fayth that they haue in Ieſus Chriſte: For as all the ſinnes of the Infidels and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>probate are mortall and irremiſſyble, becauſe of their infidelitie,<note place="margin">Hebr. 11. Ioh. 3.5.6. Roma. 8.1</note> ſo all the ſinnes of the faithfull and elect are ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niable and remiſſible, becauſe of their fayth:<note place="margin">1. Ioh. 4.5. Mark. 6. Iohn. 3.8. Roma. 8. 1. Iohn. 3.5</note> And therfore I beléeue one one<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lie ſinne to be mortall &amp; irremiſſyble, that is to ſaye, Infidelitie: That is to ſay, not to beleeue in the ſonne of God, for where true faith in Ieſus Chriſte is founde, all ſinnes are hydden, coue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red and pardoned.</p>
               </div>
            </div>
            <div type="commentary">
               <head>¶ I beleeue the reſurrection of the fleſhe, which is the ſeconde fruit of my fayth.</head>
               <div n="94" type="article">
                  <head>The .lxxxxiiii. Article.</head>
                  <p>
                     <note place="margin">Iob. 14.19. Eſai. 26. Dan. 12. 1. Cor. 15. Apoc. 20. Iohn. 5.11.</note>
                     <hi>I</hi> Beléeue a reſurrection to come, and generall vnto all the worlde, aſwell to the good as euyll: The which ſhall be done at the ende and conſum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mation of the worlde, by the vertue
<pb n="46" facs="tcp:13133:58"/> of Chriſte, and by the miniſtring of the Angels:<note place="margin">Math. 24. 1. Theſ. 4.</note> the which with a lowde Trumpet ſhall call all the worlde be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore the Lorde, and ſhall aſſemble all the elect, from the fowre windes, from the higheſt heauens, vnto the loweſt part of the earth, and ſhall ſeperate the wicked from the middeſt of the righte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous:<note place="margin">Math. 13.</note> and ſhall caſt them in the fornace of fyre, where ſhall be wéeping &amp; gna<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhing of téethe.<note place="margin">Dan. 12.</note> Then the righteous ſhall ſhyne as the Sunne, in the king<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome of their Father. And ſhalbe lyke and companions with the Angelles of God. That is the ſeconde reſurrection,<note place="margin">Math. 22. 2. Timo. 2. Apoc. 20.</note> and bleſſed is he that ſhall haue parte and portion in the ſame, for he ſhal ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer be touched with the ſecond death.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="95" type="article">
                  <head>The .lxxxxv. Article.</head>
                  <p>
                     <hi>I</hi> Beléeue that that reſurrection ſhall be done in fleſhe, and not in ſpyrite.<note place="margin">Ezech. 37. Sopho. 3. Philip. 3. Eccle. 12. Mat. 10.21 Iohn. 3.5.</note> That is to ſaye, that the ſoule or ſpyrite of man ſhall not ryſe againe, for ſo muche as it is immortall, and neuer dyeth. But the bodye, the
<pb facs="tcp:13133:59"/> which before (aſwell according to his nature,<note place="margin">2. Cor. 5. Gene. 3. Rom. 5.6.</note> as thorow ſin) was ſubiect vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to death, corrpution, rotten &amp; brought into duſt and aſhes, ſhall be rayſed vp and vnited with his ſoule and proper ſpirite,<note place="margin">1. Cor. 15.</note> and ſet in a perfecter eſtate then that of the firſt man before ſinne,<note place="margin">Gene. 2. Eccle. 17. Roma. 8. Phil. 3.</note> exempted from all corruption of ſinne, and conſequentlie from all other im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perfections, like vnto the gloryous bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dye of Chriſte.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="96" type="article">
                  <head>The .lxxxxvi. Article.</head>
                  <p>
                     <note place="margin">Iob. 19. Iohn. 5.11. Acts. 23.24. 2. Cor. 5.</note>
                     <hi>I</hi> Do alſo beléeue that I ſhall ryſe a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gaine, not in the fleſhe or body of a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nother mans, but in my very owne body, which I brought from my mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers wombe: with thoſe ſame bones, with y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> very body which I haue nowe: The ſame notwithſtanding tranſfor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med and chaunged:<note place="margin">1. Cor. 15.</note> made of mortall, immortall: of corruptible, incorrup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tible: of vyle and contemptible, glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rious.<note place="margin">Phil. 3.</note> And therefore I looke for my ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uiour Ieſus Chriſte: who thorow his vertue, ſhall tranſfigure my vile body: that it maye be lyke vnto his glorious
<pb n="47" facs="tcp:13133:59"/> body, according to y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> power, by which hee can make all thinges ſubiect vnto himſelfe.</p>
               </div>
            </div>
            <div type="commentary">
               <head>¶ I beleeue the lyfe euerlaſtyng. VVhich is the thirde and laſte fruite of my fayth.</head>
               <div n="97" type="article">
                  <head>The .lxxxxvii. Article.</head>
                  <p>
                     <hi>I</hi> Beléeue that I ſhall ryſe againe (as I haue ſayde) with all the faithfull and electe, not for to dye againe,<note place="margin">3. Reg. 17. 4. Re. 4.13. Math. 9.27 Luke. 7. Iohn. 11. Acts. 9.20. Iohn. 5.11.</note> as thoſe which were myraculouſlye ray<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed, aſwell by Chriſte, as by the Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phets and Apoſtles and ſuch other, but into an immortal, eternall and perdu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rable lyfe, for to raigne eternallye with God in body and ſoule:<note place="margin">Iohn. 3. Roma. 8. Gala. 3.4. Ephe. 1.</note> And here<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of I am very certayne and doubte no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing at all of it: knowing that who<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoeuer doubteth of his ſaluation made by Ieſus Chriſte, he ſhall neuer bee ſaued. Wherefore,<note place="margin">Roma. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>.</note> euen as I am ſure and certaine, that Chriſte is dead and roſe againe for mée, and doubt nothing
<pb facs="tcp:13133:60"/> at all therof, but am ſure and certaine of my ſaluation made by him. And that infallibly I ſhalbe ſaued,<note place="margin">Iohn. 3.5.6.8.10.</note> and ſhal go into eternall lyfe by him.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="98" type="article">
                  <head>The .lxxxxviii. Article.</head>
                  <p>
                     <note place="margin">1. Cor. 13. 1. Iohn. 3.</note>
                     <hi>I</hi> Beléeue that then I ſhall ſée face to face, him whome I do nowe ſée but by the glaſſe of fayth, &amp; ſhall know him perfectly,<note place="margin">Pſalm. 110. 1. Cor. 15.</note> whome I knowe nowe but partlye, who after that he hath deſtroyed and confounded all his ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerſaries, putting them as his foote<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtoole,<note place="margin">Eſa. 65.66. 2. Peter. 3.</note> wyll make all thinges newe, for the glorie of his choſen. And ſhall be God all in all, and in all things: Then euery one ſhall not teache his brother,<note place="margin">Apoc. 21. Ierem. 31. Hebr. 8.</note> ſaying: Knowe the Lord: For all ſhall knowe him from the greateſt to the leaſt among them.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="99" type="article">
                  <head>The .lxxxxix. Article.</head>
                  <p>
                     <note place="margin">Luke. 16. Numb. 16.</note>
                     <hi>I</hi> Doo alſo beléeue that as the ſoules and ſpyrites of the Infidels, wicked
<pb n="48" facs="tcp:13133:60"/> and reprobate,<note place="margin">1. Peter. 3. 2. Peter. 2. Iude. 1. Apoc. 20.</note> after they are departed from the body: that ſtrayght way they deſcende into hell, in the eternall fyre of hell, their bodies remayning in the earth corrupted and rotten: So the ſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rites and ſoules of the faithfull,<note place="margin">Luke. 23. Iohn. 5.6.8.11.17. 2. Cor. 5. Philip. 1.</note> and e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lect children of God aſſoone as they de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>part from their body, without tarying any whytte, doo go ſtrayght way into heauen into glorye with the Lorde. And there doo looke for alwayes with great deſyre,<note place="margin">Roma. 1. Luke. 21.</note> the comming and totall redemption of their bodyes, the which they haue left rotten and corrupted in the earth, the which they ſhall obtaine at the latter daye, and not before. Wherein I reiect the foolyſh opinion,<note place="margin">Colloſ. 3. Ierene<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="3 letters">
                           <desc>•••</desc>
                        </gap>. S. Chriſo. S. Barna<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>.</note> of the dreamers (although there be of the auncients and excellent Authors) which affirme y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſpirites of the Saints not to be yet in heauen, but to ſléepe in a certaine place, to vs vnknowen, vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tyll they hauing receyued theyr bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dyes at the latter daye,<note place="margin">Ephe. 4.</note> in which the myſticall body of Chriſt being entyer, perfect and fulfilled, ought to enter in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to eternall glory.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="100" type="article">
                  <pb facs="tcp:13133:61"/>
                  <head>The .C. Article.</head>
                  <p>FInally, I beléeue that as y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> Saints and bleſſed (the Iudgement be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing done) doo go with Chriſte triumphing in the ayre in body and ſoule, for to abyde eternally in glorie with him, and his Angelles. That ſo the wicked, myſerable and dampned, ſhall go into hel in body and ſoule with the diuell and his angels, for to abyde there eternally, and to be tormen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted with him in hell fire, which neuer goeth out, where is wéeping and gna<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhing of teethe, where the woorme ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer dyeth. From which the Lorde preſerue and kéepe vs thorowe his grace and mercie. <hi>Amen.</hi>
                  </p>
               </div>
            </div>
         </div>
         <div type="conclusion">
            <pb facs="tcp:13133:61"/>
            <head>
               <g ref="char:leaf">❧</g> The Concluſion.</head>
            <p>BEholde (my déere and welbeloued brethren in Ieſus Chriſt) briefly, the fayth &amp; knowledge of the my<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſteries which the Lorde hath geuen and beſtowed vppon mee thorowe his grace and mercy, vnworthy and poore ſinner, which haue not meryted ſo much good<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe towardes him, but rather his wrath and iudgement: And therfore I know and confeſſe all to haue procée<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded from him, vnto whom onely I ren<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der eternall thankes, whome alſo I be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſéeche in the name of his Sonne Ieſus Chriſt our Lord, to preſerue &amp; kéepe me thorow his holy ſpirit, in that faith vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to the ende, &amp; to geue mee grace, vertue &amp; power to confeſſe it with the hart and mouth, aſwell before the Infidelles, as the faithfull, the tyrants and hangmen of Antechriſt, &amp; to mayntaine the ſame vnto the laſt drop of my blood: I deſire greatly to lyue and dye in y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> faith, kno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wing &amp; being well aſſured, that it hath for her fou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>dation the only word of God, and that in y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſame al the holy Fathers, Patriarkes, Prophets and Apoſtles of
<pb facs="tcp:13133:62"/> Ieſus Chriſt haue liued and dyed in it. That is y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> true knowledge of the Lord, the which conſyſteth in the beatytude and felicitie of man, as Chriſte ſayth in the Goſpell, This is lyfe eternall (O Father) that we acknowledge thée to be very God,<note place="margin">Iohn. 17.</note> and him whom thou haſt ſent Ieſus Chriſte. This is the auncient doctrine nowe reuealed by the holy ſpy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rite, the which in our tyme was rayſed vp againe, and as from the bottome of the depthes was reſtored vnto vs a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gaine, by the grace and mercye of God, and by the myniſtring of good Doctors, and true faythfull Myniſters of the ſame. This is the hydden trueth, the which was buryed and kepte cloſe by that Antechriſte of Rome, and his falſe Prophets, theſe fiue hundreth yéeres or there about: who in ſtéede thereof dyd auaunce their dreaminges and mans traditions, and other lyke doctrine fry<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uolous, vaine and vnprofitable, to the great diſhonor of God, to the offending of the faythfull, and to the ruyne of all the Churche of Ieſus Chriſte: As alſo they doo yet at this daye in many places thorowe out the world, perſecuting that
<pb facs="tcp:13133:62"/> holy Euangelicall doctrine, in all places and by all meanes. Endeuoring them ſelues to burie it againe, to hyde and couer it, and altogether to deſtroye it, but they ſhall all periſh in their enter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>priſes,<note place="margin">Eſai. 49.</note> and the worde of the Goſpell ſhall abyde eternally: For ſo hath hée promiſed,<note place="margin">Luke. 1.</note> who is onely true and can not lye, And heauen and earth ſhall ſooner paſſe, then his promiſe ſhoulde not hée fulfilled.<note place="margin">Math. 10.</note> Wherefore bleſſed is hée that ſhall continue vnto the ende in that doc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trine. For he ſhall be partaker of all the promiſes of God: And on the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trarie, wo be vnto him that ſhall con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tempne, deſpyſe or reiecte it. For the wrath of God abydeth vpon him. Hée that beléeueth in mée (ſayth Chriſte) hee ſhall not bée condempned.<note place="margin">Iohn. 3.</note> But hée that beléeueth not, hee is alreadye condempned, his parte and portion ſhall be with the peruerſe and wycked Hypocrites, in eternall hell fyre.</p>
            <p>Alſo I reiecte alwayes the doctryne of <hi>Luiterim,</hi> with whome I wyll haue neyther parte nor portion. And alſo I renownce all the doctryne
<pb facs="tcp:13133:63"/> of that Antechriſt of Rome, with al his Idolatries, mans ſectes, errors and pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>piſticall ſuperſtitions, in which, I haue bene ſome tyme plunged in it (to my great hurte) euen vp to the eares, abu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing my ſelfe after the creatures, forſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king my Creator, perſecuting (yea, eue<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> vnto death) thoſe which dyd teache that ſame which I now beléeue and confes. But I haue obtained mercy of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> Lord,<note place="margin">1. Tim. 1.</note> becauſe I dyd it thorow ignoraunce, in my vnbeléefe, as many do yet at this day thorowe out the worlde, being lead and conducted with a fooliſh &amp; vndiſcrete zeale: who in accuſing, perſecuting and putting to death the faithfull, and true members of Ieſus Chriſte (which doo ſeeke nothing elſe but the honor of God, and the ſaluation of all the worlde,) doo thinke to doo things agréeable to God,<note place="margin">Iohn. 16.</note> and to offer vnto him great Sacrifices: whome I deſire not to be ſo wylful and raſh in iudgement, but to examine it neerer, and to ſearche and trye the mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter better, before they take any thing in hande. To the ende they be not one day conſtrained to ſay &amp; confeſſe, that which I nowe confeſſe of my ſelfe, that they
<pb facs="tcp:13133:63"/> haue ſhamefully erred and ſinned. (But thinking they dyd well, notwithſtan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding) in perſecuting my good Lorde, maiſter, and onely ſauior Ieſus Chriſt. For that which I haue done vnto his members and faithfull (whome then I eſteemed as Heretickes, ſeditious, and blaſphemers of God and of his worde, where they were louers thereof,) I doo eſteeme that I dyd it vnto him ſelfe. For hee ſayth in the Goſpell,<note place="margin">Math. 25.</note> that that which men do vnto thoſe which beleeue in him, hee eſteemeth it to be done vnto himſelfe, be it good or euyll.<note place="margin">Acts. 9.</note> The which he hath afterwards confirmed to <hi>Paul,</hi> perſecuting his Church after his aſcen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cion. I then knowing the great errors, abuſes, and ſuperſtitions, wherein I was plunged beforetyme. Nowe I re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nounce and forſake all Idolatryes and falſe doctrines, which are contrary and againſt the doctrine of my maiſter Ie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſus Chriſte, which is the holy and pure worde of God, contained in the canoni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>call bookes of the olde and newe Teſta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>me<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t, reuealed by the holy Ghoſt:<note place="margin">2. Peter. 1.</note> whom I take for my guide and leader, for to dyrect and leade me in this mortall life,
<pb facs="tcp:13133:64"/> as the pyller of fyre dyd leade the chyl<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren of Iſraell thorowe the wyldernes into the lande of promiſe.<note place="margin">Exo. 12..</note> That ſhall be the Lanterne vnto my feete.<note place="margin">Pſal. 119.</note> Fur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thermore, I promiſe from hencefoorth, and for the reſidue of my lyfe, to walke and lyue according to that doctrine, the beſt I can poſſyble: hauing the ſpirite of God, who ſhall aſſyſt and dyrect mee in all my wayes, without whome I can doo nothing, with which I can doo all thinges,<note place="margin">Philip. 4.</note> inſomuch that all ſhall be to the prayſe of the Lorde, to the ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uauncement of the kyngdome of his ſonne, and to the edifycation of all the Churche, and to the ſaluation of my ſoule. The which moſt humbly &amp; with all my harte I require,<note place="margin">Math. 6.</note> of that good fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther which is aboue in the heauens, that his name maye bee in vs and thorowe vs ſanctified, as hee is holye in him ſelfe: And that his kingdome come, ſo that hee doo raygne perfectlie ouer vs, and we maye obey his worde, and com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maundement: That his wyll be done here belowe in earth, as it is done by the Angelles aboue in heauen. Be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeeching him alſo thorowe Ieſus Chriſt
<pb facs="tcp:13133:64"/> his Sonne our Lorde, to geue and ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>myniſter vnto mee in this mortall life, all thinges neceſſarie,<note place="margin">Deut, 8. Math. 4.</note> aſwell to the Soule as body, admyniſtring vnto me euerie daye the daylye breade of his worde, without which my ſoule can not lyue.<note place="margin">Prou. 24. Roma. 7.</note> And becauſe I am a ſyn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner by nature, corrupte, ſolde vnder ſinne, not able to doo none other thing but to ſinne, and that I offende more then there be dayes, I beſeeche him not to enter into iudgement with mee, ney<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther correcte and puniſhe me according to my merytes and deſertes, but mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cifullye pardon mee all my offences a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt him committed, as I doo pardon all thoſe which haue offended mee: And looke vppon mee, not in mee, but in the face of his ſonne Ieſus Chriſte, thorow whoſe meanes I finde grace and mercy before him, and before his righteous iudgement: I beſeech him alwayes to aſſiſt me thorowe his holye ſpirite, by which I may eſcape the aſſault and em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>buſhments of the world, the fleſh and of Satan: to ſurmou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t alwayes &amp; vanquiſh their aſſaults and temptations, without
<pb facs="tcp:13133:65"/> being broken or ouercome in any thing: That their ſnares and cords being bro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken, I maye gloriouſly eſcape: and by that meanes I ſhall know plainly, that bee is the King of Kinges,<note place="margin">Apoc. 19.</note> and Lorde o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer all Lordes, onely God, ſage, im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mortal, and inuyſible, altogether migh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie, ſtrong and glorious: vnto whom onelye appertayneth the kyng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome, the power and the glorie, for euer and euer. <hi>Amen.</hi>
            </p>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
            <closer>
               <dateline>
                  <date>
                     <hi>26. Februarie. 1577.</hi>
                  </date>
               </dateline>
            </closer>
            <pb facs="tcp:13133:65"/>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
